<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A cordiall of comfort To preserue the heart, from fainting with griefe or feare: for our friends, or our owne visitation, by the plague. Also a thankes-giuing to almightie God, for staying the visitation in London, and the suburbs thereof. Both which may be of vse to Christians in other places, that are cleere, visited, or recouered. By William Chibald.</title>
            <author>Chibald, William, 1575-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118343</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853550</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853550</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18937</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18603)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18937)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1198:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A cordiall of comfort To preserue the heart, from fainting with griefe or feare: for our friends, or our owne visitation, by the plague. Also a thankes-giuing to almightie God, for staying the visitation in London, and the suburbs thereof. Both which may be of vse to Christians in other places, that are cleere, visited, or recouered. By William Chibald.</title>
                  <author>Chibald, William, 1575-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 110 [i.e. 120], [10], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By W. I[ones] for Nic. Bourne and Edw. Brewster, and are to be sold at the Royall Exchange, and at the Bible in Pauls-Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>"An humble thanks-giuing to Almightie God" has separate dated title page and pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Page 120 is misnumbered 110.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A CORDIALL OF COMFORT.</p>
                  <p>To preſerue the Heart, from fainting with Griefe or Feare: for our Friends, or our owne Viſitation, by the Plague.</p>
                  <p>Alſo a Thankeſ-giuing to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, for ſtaying the Viſitation in <hi>London,</hi> and the Subvrbs thereof.</p>
                  <p>Both which may be of vſe to Chriſtians in other places, that are cleere, viſited, or recouered.</p>
                  <p>BY WILLIAM CHIBALD.</p>
                  <p>Printed at London by <hi>W. I.</hi> for <hi>Nic. Bourn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>Edw. Brewſter,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Royall Exchange, and at the Bible in Pauls-Church-yard. 1625.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:2"/>
                  <head>TO The Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull; the Company of the <hi>Lether-Sellers:</hi> The Maſters and Wardens; The Aſſiſtants and Liuery, with the reſt of the Brethren, of that worthy Societie.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Right Worſhipfull, and Worthy:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of bookes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to perſons of place and qualitie, is
<pb facs="tcp:18937:3"/> to manifeſt a ſeruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able reſpect and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence vnto them; and to ſupplicate a fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſpect, and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from them.</p>
                  <p>According to theſe fayre endes, I haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured to deuote this my Treatiſe, which doth need the one, to your Worſhips that are worthy of the other.</p>
                  <p>You are worthy of my Dedication in two reſpects (namely) as Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, and as Lether-Sellers
<pb facs="tcp:18937:3"/> of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. As Citizens, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I wrote it in the Viſitation of the City; and for the comfort of Citizens, in the Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As Lether-ſellers, becauſe you are that Company, whereof my deare Father was, Mr. <hi>Iames Chibald,</hi> (of ſweet memory I hope among you) who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeere 1595. was Maſter, &amp; head of your Body, euen as his
<pb facs="tcp:18937:4"/> eldeſt Sonne, my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Brother, is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing member of the ſame at this day.</p>
                  <p>It remaynes, that your Worſhips would be pleaſed, by accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſeruice of this Dedication, to Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the Booke: The rather, ſeeing the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ayme in dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating it to you, is, but to honour you that are liuing, by my deare Parent that is dead: and to honour
<pb facs="tcp:18937:4"/> the memory of him that is abſent, by you that are preſent, which as Brethren of one Company, and Parents of Children, you cannot but ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue.</p>
                  <p>That you may the more freely grant my requeſt, I pray you to take vnto your conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration further, the ſubiect matter of the Booke: which is Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Phyſicke. For it preſcribes you, firſt, a
<pb facs="tcp:18937:5"/> Cordiall: Secondly, a Dyet.</p>
                  <p>The Cordiall hath a twofold nature. 1. To preſerue your bodyes from infection or death by the Plague (if the Lord ſee it good for your ſoules, and as Chriſtians you ſhould not deſire it otherwiſe.) 2. To keep your ſoules from fainting, with immoderate Griefe or Feare for your Friends, or your owne Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Plague.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:5"/>
                  <p>The Dyet is, to teach you that ſuruiue, how to liue to GODS glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by learning to bee thankefull to God for your own preſeruation, and for Gods wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and mercifull ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſickneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. Both which as men, and Chriſtian men, you haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to looke after and learne.</p>
                  <p>In hope of your free fauor herein, I humbly take my leaue, with my
<pb facs="tcp:18937:6"/> heartie prayer vnto God, to bleſſe the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of my Treatiſe to your Corporall and Spirituall health in Ieſus Chriſt, in whom I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips moſt bounden in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſeruice, <hi>WILLIAM CHIBALD.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:6"/>
                  <head>To the Chriſtian Reader, that needs Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Phyſicke from the Word, againſt Griefe, or Feare, by reaſon of the Plague.</head>
                  <p>IN the beginning of the Creation,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.2.</note> 
                     <hi>when dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was vpon the deepe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6.</note> 
                     <hi>the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the light to ſhine out of darkneſſe.</hi> As vnlikely effect of ſuch a cauſe as the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one ſee, that was
<pb facs="tcp:18937:7"/> borne blind,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.11.</note> by <hi>anointing his eyes with clay and ſpittle;</hi> which was more likely to put them out, if euer hee had any ſight.</p>
                  <p>Not long ſince, there was darkneſſe and heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vpon the face of my Family, by reaſon of Gods Viſitation, and (behold) out of the darknes of that ſorrow, Almightie GOD hath brought forth this Light of Spirituall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort.</p>
                  <p>After a ſort, I may truly ſay, GOD hath commaunded it to ſhine
<pb facs="tcp:18937:7"/> forth, partly by his ſpeciall aſsiſtance, when J was (in my ſelfe) very vnfyt for ſtudy, and partly by his prouidence in ſtirring vp many to bee very inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue to ſeeke after it, and to bee very importunate for the publiſhing thereof.</p>
                  <p>J neuer intended to <hi>put this Light vnder a Buſhell</hi> wholly to couer it:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.15</note> for J did <hi>ſet it vpon a Candleſticke</hi> to giue light in one roome (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to my Pariſhioners, kindred, and friends to
<pb facs="tcp:18937:8"/> whom J gaue ſome Copies: But now at the inſtance of many, J haue put it into a Lanthorne &amp; hung it out, in the open ſtreets for the benefit of all paſſengers.</p>
                  <p>J confeſſe the light is but ſmall it giues, but J hope it will burne cleere, and ſweet: the Treatiſe (J truſt) wil be free from errour, and offence.</p>
                  <p>J acknowledge alſo, that it is hung out ſomewhat late in the Euening, when many are at reſt in their graues by the Viſitation:
<pb facs="tcp:18937:8"/> but (the truth is) my tynder was wet, J could not ſtrike fyer to light it ſooner, and when it was lighted, J could not get it hung vp any ſooner.</p>
                  <p>My meaning is, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe of my heart for Gods viſytation, on the Citie, my Congregation, and my Family was ſome let to the penning of it: and the difficultie of get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Work men to print it, was a great hinderance to the publiſhing thereof any ſooner.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:9"/>
                  <p>Now that it is fyni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and publiſhed my requeſt is to the Chriſtian Reader, that hee vvould not <hi>cloſe his eyes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.19</note> that hee cannot ſee the light, but open them to <hi>walke by it,</hi> to the end hee may not ſtumble and fal, at im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate Griefe or Feare by reaſon of his own, or his friendes Viſytation by the Plague.</p>
                  <p>And my humble Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is: That hee, who <hi>is the true Light,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.9</note> 
                     <hi>that lighteneth euery one
<pb facs="tcp:18937:9"/> which commeth into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he world,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reuel.</hi> 1.13</note> and who <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the midſt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>euen golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks:</hi> That he would be graciouſly pleaſed to adde further light &amp; life to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eading &amp; peruſing of my Treatiſe, for the glory of God, and the good of his Church; and let all that read it for their comfort, ſay with me, <hi>Amen.</hi> Euen as J will ſay with all that find comfort by the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it, <hi>The Lord bee praiſed</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours in the ſeruice of your Faith <hi>W. C.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:10"/>
                  <head>A Table ſhewing the Contents of this Booke.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>WHen teares for ſin proue godly pag, <hi>4.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How to comfort our ſelues againſt greife for the viſitation of our fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. pag. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How to comfort our ſelues againſt greife for our viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion p. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The nature of the affliction of Gods children. p. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The cauſes of their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, efficient and mouing. pa. <hi>13. 14. 15.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Companion of it. p. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18937:10"/>
                     <item>The end of it, intent and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. p. <hi>18. &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How to hearten our ſelues againſt the feare of the plague. pa. <hi>24.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How you may lawfully feare the plague. pa. <hi>32, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How you may not feare the plague. pa, <hi>35.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The plague is no ſigne of Gods eternall anger to the godly, p. <hi>43.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sixe meanes to preuent the infestiion of the plague. p. <hi>48.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The <hi>1.</hi> meanes, p. <hi>48.</hi> the <hi>2.</hi> in p. <hi>50.</hi> the <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>51.</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> in p. <hi>53.</hi> the <hi>5</hi> p. <hi>55.</hi> the <hi>6</hi> p. <hi>66.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sixe meanes to keep us from dying of the plague. p. <hi>57.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The <hi>1</hi> meanes p. <hi>58.</hi> the <hi>2</hi> in pa. <hi>59.</hi> the <hi>3</hi> in pa. <hi>60.</hi> the <hi>4</hi> in pa. <hi>64.</hi> the <hi>5</hi> in pag <hi>65.</hi> the <hi>6</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:18937:11"/> meanes in pa. <hi>66.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cautions touching the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie of theſe meanes, to keepe vs frrm infection or death by the plague. pa. <hi>68. &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Reaſons to proue that the godly doe dy in Gods fauour though the dy of the plague<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pag. <hi>74.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How that comes to paſſe page <hi>81.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>What makes death bleſſed or accurſſed to men. pa. <hi>84.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Rules to know how we ſhal dy in Gods fauour, though we dy of the plague. pa. <hi>74. 86.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>The firſt pa. <hi>86.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The ſecond pa. <hi>92</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The third pa. <hi>96.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The fourth pag. <hi>99.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The fift p. <hi>101.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>The ſixt pa. <hi>102.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18937:11"/>
                     <item>Seuen holy vertues or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns to be done by Chriſtians, to aſſure them of Gods fauour and loue in life and death. pag. <hi>107</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A diſtinction of the ſauing graces of the Spirit wrought in the Elect. pag.</item>
                     <item>What brings vs into the eſtate of grace, and what keeps vs therein. p. <hi>108.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A farewell to them that haue not been viſited. p. <hi>118.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A farewel to them that haue been viſited, and yet are eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. p. <hi>118.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A farewell to both ſorts. pag. <hi>119.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="approbation">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:12"/>
                  <head>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. FEATLIES Approbation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Haue peruſed this Treatiſe, and fynd it very ſound for Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and ſeaſonable for the time; and hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued much comfort by it my ſelfe, J deſyre others may do the like by the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther publiſhing thereof.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>DANIEL FEATLY.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18937:12"/>
                  <head>A SPIRITV all Cordiall, againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F late it hath pleaſed God to viſite my Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Vpon this occaſion (according to good order) <hi>I am</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 36.5</note> 
                     <hi>ſhut vp</hi> in my Church yard: and by this meanes I may not (without offence) go abroad, either to <hi>the houſe of God</hi> to teach my people, or to my freinds houſes, to ſee how they doe: but (bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God (that <hi>in iudgment remembers mercy</hi>) ſixe of nine perſons<note n="b" place="margin">Abac. 3.2</note> 
                     <hi>remaine eſcaped, as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18937:13"/> it is this day</hi> from death,<note place="margin">Ezra, 9.15</note> and foure of nine from infection.</p>
                  <p>Though God haue impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned my body: yet hath he enlarged my ſpirit, though he hath ſilenced my tongue, and thereby taken from me liberty to preach: yet hath he put my pen into my hand, and thereby given me an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to write ſome ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall counſell, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of my dearly beloved &amp; like loving neighbours, and Pariſhioners, and my kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and friends, that are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected &amp; afflicted with Gods viſitation on vs. As alſo for their conſolation that haue been, are: or may be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, by meanes of the like viſitation.</p>
                  <p>That which I haue now written vnto you is that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18937:13"/> which will be beſt for you to reade, and that will be beſt for you to read at this time, which will beſt meet with, and remoue that, which doth now moſt trouble you name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Griefe and feare.</p>
                  <p>That you are grieued for me and mine, and for our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, I aſſuredly beleeue. And becauſe I beleeue it, therefore haue I writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe few leaues &amp; lines,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 11 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0</note> to aſſwage your ſorrow: for it were hard, if my affliction ſhould make a wound of griefe in your hearts, and I not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make a playſter of comfort to heale it. Farre be ſuch ingratitude from me, and farre bee ſuch a want from you.</p>
                  <p>Though, in ſome reſpects I am grived with your ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18937:14"/> yet in other regards I reioyce. not ſimply, for the griefe it ſelfe: but for that which (I know) is the cauſe, and that which (I hope) will be the fruite, and that which (I pray) may be the iſſue of it.</p>
                  <p>The cauſe of your griefe for vs is your loue; for when the Iewes ſaw, how Chriſt wept for <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oh. 11.36</note> they ſaid, <hi>behold how he loued him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fruite, is godly ſorrow for ſinne;<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eares <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or ſin proue godly.</note> or repentance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to amendment of life and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: and indeed then ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row or teares proue godly, when they exerciſe a twofold nature they haue, namely, 1. A ſalt brackiſh or briniſh quality. 2. A wet or moyſt qualitie. The ſalt or briniſh qualitie of ſorrow or teares
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18937:14"/> ſhewes it ſelfe to be godly, 1. when it Seaſons the ſoule with grace, 2. When it eates out the corrupt humour of wickednes that is in it, and 3 keepes the heart from pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifiyng in ſin. The moyſt &amp; wet qualitie that is in teares: doth ſhew it ſelfe to be god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when 1. it ſoftens the heart that is hardned<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 3.13.</note> 
                     <hi>with the deceitefulnes of ſinne,</hi> and 2. when it<note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 4.14</note> 
                     <hi>waſheth the heart from wickednes</hi> and<note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>clenſeth it</hi> from the loue of ſenſuall pleaſures.</p>
                  <p>The iſſue which (I pray) may come of your ſorrow for me, is an aſſurance to your ſoules, that you are living, and not dead members of the Chriſtian body, in that you <hi rend="sup">g</hi> 
                     <hi>can be touched with the feeling of our infirmities.<note place="margin">Heb. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Rom. 12.15</note> Weepe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18937:15"/> with them that weep.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 4.5</note> 
                     <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber them that are in bonds, as if you were bound with them.</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5</note> And <hi>pittie your brethren when the hand of the Lord toucheth them.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 13.3.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 19 21</note> In theſe reſpects I hope I may ſay with the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Now I reioyce, not that yee were made ſorry: but that yee ſorrowed to repentance for yee were made ſorry after a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner, that yee might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue damage by vs in nothing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But (to omit any longer preface,) and to come to the matter intended, which is remouing of your griefe and feare.</p>
                  <p>Againſt your griefe I will propound, 1. matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. 2. Meditations of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, (the good Lord reach and apply it, by his Spirit, vnto your Spirits, according
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18937:15"/> to the nature of the doctrine it ſelfe; and according to my deſire &amp; minde in propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it.)</p>
                  <p>That you may be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the hand of Gods viſitation vpon my Family,<note place="margin">How to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues with Gods viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion on our f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>amily.</note> I pray you take notice of, and conſider ſeriouſly theſe fiue points.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 That we are not able to reſiſt the hand of God, for <hi>we are</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">k</hi> 
                     <hi>not ſtronger then he?</hi> Wee are in this reſpect <hi>but</hi> I <hi>as clay in the hands of the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> for <hi>the</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.22. Ier. 18.6. Dan. 4.35</note> 
                     <hi>Lord doth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will in the armie of heauen, and among the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the earth and none can ſtay his hand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 That we haue moſt iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerued to drinke of this cup with others <hi rend="sup">b</hi> 
                     <hi>wee haue accepted the puniſhment of our
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18937:16"/> iniquitie.</hi> For <hi>we haue ſinned againſt God and therefore muſt we beare</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Micah 7</note> 
                     <hi>the hand of the Lord, we indeed iuſtly receiue the due reward of our deedes.</hi> Yea, we muſt <hi>be anmbe &amp; not open our mouthes, becauſe it is his doing, who hath not done without cauſe</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Levit. 26</note> 
                     <hi>all that he hath done vnto vs.</hi> and therefore<note n="e" place="margin">Luk 23.</note> 
                     <hi>the Lord is iuſt for wee haue deſerued to haue ben beneath for our ſinnes.</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 39.</note> For who are we? And what is our Fathers houſe, that in ſuch a common calamity we ſhould looke to be free? See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note n="g" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>the time is come that iudg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment muſt begin at the houſe of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That we are not alone in this affliction, for we haue fellowes enough (too many if the Lord ſaw it good)<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> 
                     <hi>There hath no tentation taken
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18937:16"/> vs: but ſuch as is common to man.</hi> The <hi>Lord hath</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">2. Sam. 7.14.</note> 
                     <hi>chaſtened vs with the rod of men, and with the ſtripes of the children of men:</hi> yea, with the ſtripes of them that are his owne children.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That all in our family haue not bin ſmitten (as yet) but a few onely; nor are they all dead that were ſmitten, but ſome onely, nor were they all ſmitten together: but by degrees &amp; ſucceſſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly only. Firſt, our ſeruants, and then our children; nor with ſo heauie a ſtroke as ſome haue bin, but gently &amp; with moderation,<note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 30.11. &amp; 10.24</note> 
                     <hi>with mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and iudgement</hi> the Lord be praiſed therefore.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. And laſtly, conſider, that none of vs haue wanted that which many (our bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18937:17"/> haue beene without, namely, food and phyſicke: helpers and keepers, varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of roomes and chambers, with other conueniences: ſo that I may truely ſay (to Gods glory, our benefit, and your content) of our ſelues, as <hi>Paul</hi> did of himſelfe and companions in affliction: <hi>We are</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.9.</note> 
                     <hi>as dying, and behold we liue,</hi> as <hi>chaſtened; but not kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> and in another place,<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.8.</note> 
                     <hi>We are troubled on euery ſide: but not diſtreſſed. Wee are in doubt: but not in deſpaire.</hi> And with <hi>Dauid,</hi> the <hi rend="sup">n</hi> 
                     <hi>Lord hath thruſt ſore at vs, but hath not giuen vs ouer vnto death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is true, I haue parted with a good ſeruant &amp; good childe: and a good Curate, My faithfull fellow helper in the miniſtery, but it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18937:17"/> to vs they were not too good for him that gaue them their goodnes, and that had more right to them then I, for God, <hi>in heauen</hi> was <hi rend="sup">o</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the one, <hi rend="sup">p</hi> 
                     <hi>Father</hi> to the other, and <hi rend="sup">q</hi> 
                     <hi>Arch-Paſtor</hi> and <hi>Biſhop</hi> to the other, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore might command them. And it is a comfort to vs, &amp; ſo it may be to you, that <hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>the Lord is better to vs then tenne ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2. Sam. 1 3.</note> as <hi>Elkanah</hi> ſaid that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was to his wife <hi>Annah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now leaſt (haply) content may ſeeme to ſome but a dry plaiſter for ſuch a running ſore, not broad enough to couer it, or not ſoueraigne enough to heale it; therfore (to make a perfect cure) I haue thought of another medicine for the malady; and ſo I paſſe on to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18937:18"/> ſort of meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that may giue you comfort (as well as content) againſt your heauineſſe for our viſitation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">How to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt griefe for our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation.</note>Theſe comforts ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from ſeuerall conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions concerning our afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as namely, 1. The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it. 2. The Cauſe of it. 3. The Effect of it. 4. The Companion of it. 5. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the End of it. For in all theſe points there lieth mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of comfort; from all theſe haue the faithful raiſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to themſelues in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and withall theſe haue wee comforted our ſelues in our viſitation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Nature of this viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is the ſame with the nature of all other afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the godly:<note place="margin">The nature of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of the godly.</note> which is, not to be a vengeance of God
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18937:18"/> to wreake his fury on vs to our vtter deſtruction: but to be a<note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 12.5, 6, 7. 1. Cor. 11.32.</note> 
                     <hi>chatiſtment and correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to make vs repent more ſoundly of our paſt ſinnes, and to prevent with more watchfulneſſe the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſame, or like ſins againe,<note place="margin">Reu. 3.19.</note> that<note n="c" place="margin">Reu 2.29.</note> 
                     <hi>we may be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and amend.</hi> Indeed, it is in it ſelfe a puniſhment, and to the wicked that repent not, it is a vengeance: but to the godly that amend, it is not ſo, as ſhall bee proued more at large hereafter. And therefore in this reſpect may we all take comfort in it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 The cauſe of this our viſitation is twofold,<note place="margin">The cauſes of the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the godly.</note> Effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and impulſiue. The Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cauſe is the author or ſender of it, which is God, and herein God is <hi rend="sup">d</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18937:19"/> not ſimply, as God onely: but as God<note n="a" place="margin">2. Sam. 7 14.</note> 
                     <hi>our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> or as mercifull. For by this viſitation <hi>wee fall into Gods hands, whoſe</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">2. Sam. 4 14</note> 
                     <hi>mercies are great:</hi> and herein <hi>GOD</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Heb 12.7</note> 
                     <hi>deals with vs, as with his ſons and daughters.</hi> Therefore <hi>wee ought not to</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>faint when vvee are rebuked of him:</hi> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently bee comfortable therein.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond cauſe is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſiue, or that which moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth God thus to afflict or chaſten vs, which is his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall loue in Chriſt. For as <hi>many as the Lord loues hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes and chaſtens.</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Reu. 3.19</note> The Lord may <hi>chaſten vs with the</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">2 Sam. 7.4, 15.</note> 
                     <hi>rod of men, and vvith the ſtripes of the children of men but his mercy ſhall not depart from vs.</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18937:19"/> So that,<note n="g" place="margin">Phil. 2.1.</note> 
                     <hi>if there be any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in loue,</hi> that is, in Gods loue, then may wee comfort our ſelues in our affliction which proceeds from it.</p>
                  <p>It is true, the Inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall cauſe of this our viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hath been Gods Angell, or infection by men: but the ſupreme Efficient is GOD. It is true alſo, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our ſinnes, the <hi rend="sup">h</hi> 
                     <hi>anger</hi> and <hi>fury</hi> of GOD may bee ſayde to bee an Impulſiue or moouing cauſe of it.<note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam. 24 1.</note> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. 10 19</note> But it is but his <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary anger, vvhich is but for a</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">i</hi> 
                     <hi>moment:</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 54.8.</note> VVhich may and doth well ſtand with his eternal loue, <hi>&amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting compaſsion</hi> in Chriſt, with which wee are to bee comforted.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18937:20"/>
                     <note place="margin">The effect of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</note>3 The effect and fruit that comes to the faithfull by all their affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tions, <hi>when they are exerciſed thereby,</hi> is very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fortable: it is the <hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                     <hi>peaceable fruite of righteouſnes:</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Heb 5.8</note> (that is) increaſe of holineſſe, both in heart &amp; life, which will bring forth true qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et and peace to the ſoule, though the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and outward man,<note n="h" place="margin">Heb 6.9.</note> be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted &amp; afflicted with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the preſent it is to <hi rend="sup">c</hi> 
                     <hi>learne obedience by the things we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer:</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Hoſ. 6.1.</note> it is to<note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 12.12.</note> 
                     <hi>returne to God that ſmites vs,</hi> and be <hi>zealous and amend.</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Reu. 3.29.</note> So that we having in ſome meaſure (through Gods grace) fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theſe fruits and effects wrought in vs by our affliction, and theſe bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing comfortable, becauſe they be ſuch as <hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>accompany ſaluation,</hi> therfore ought you
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18937:20"/> not to <hi>ſorrow</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">f</hi> 
                     <hi>as men without hope,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.18.</note> 
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 2.18.</note> like <hi>Rachell that would not be comforted:</hi> but even in griefe to remember comfort, in him, as God hath in iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment remembred mercy for vs.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 The Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affliction of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note place="margin">The comda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their affliction.</note> it is inward Spirituall conſolation, at one time or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in one kind or other, or in one meaſure or other, wherein alſo wee haue had our ſhare (bleſſed bee God.) <hi>For as the</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.5.</note> 
                     <hi>ſufferings of Chriſt abound in them: ſo their conſolations alſo abound in Chriſt. There</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal 97.</note> 
                     <hi>is light ſowen for the righteous, and ioy for the vpright in heart.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1.5.</note> And that which is ſowne for them.<note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 6 9</note> 
                     <hi>They ſhall reape in due time if they faint not:</hi> the Lord Ieſus
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18937:21"/> 
                     <hi>will not</hi>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Ioh 14 18.</note> 
                     <hi>leaue them comfort<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe:</hi> hee <hi>will not</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">1. Cor 10 13.</note> 
                     <hi>ſuffer them to bee tempted aboue that they be able to beare:</hi> hee hath<note n="n" place="margin">Ioa. 16.33.</note> 
                     <hi>bidden them to bee of good comfort,</hi> becauſe, though they <hi>ſhall haue afflictions in the world:</hi> yet <hi>ſhall haue peace in him.</hi> For though<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 30.</note> 
                     <hi>heauineſſe may endure for a night: ioy ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l come in the morning.</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Hoſ. 6.2.</note> After <hi>two dayes hee will reuiue vs, in the third day hee will raiſe vs vp, and we ſhal liue in his ſight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The laſt thing to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in our affliction, is the end of it: which is the ſame with the end of all the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the godly. And this end is twofold. 1. Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in ſending of them. 2. The event of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when they are ſent. For both theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter comfort.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18937:21"/>1. The end or intent of GOD in afflicting his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, is generally their good. For euen in them, <hi rend="sup">i</hi> 
                     <hi>God is good to Iſrael.</hi> More eſpecially God intends to them therein theſe good things, namely, 1. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of himſelfe, to make <hi>them</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">heb. 12.10.</note> 
                     <hi>partakers of his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> 2. In reſpect of Chriſt, that they may haue<note n="l" place="margin">Phil. 3.10</note> 
                     <hi>fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with his ſufferings, and bee made conformable to his death.</hi> 3. In reſpect of the wicked, that<note n="m" place="margin">1 Cor. 11 33.</note> 
                     <hi>they may nor be condemned with the world.</hi> And fourthly, in reſpect of themſelues,<note n="n" place="margin">Heb 12.</note> 
                     <hi>that they may liue,</hi> namely in heauen, and there <hi>bee glorified vvith Chriſt,</hi> when firſt they <hi>haue</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 8.17</note> 
                     <hi>ſuffered with him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:18937:22"/>2 The end or euent like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe which according to Gods intent follows vpon all the afflictions of the godly, it is comfortable, for general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is their good, ſo <hi>Dauid</hi> found it, when he ſaid, <hi>It is good for me that I haue been af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted.</hi> More particularly, theſe good things inſue thereupon: namely, 1. grace,<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 119 7.</note> 
                     <hi>better to learne Gods Statutes and to keepe his word.</hi> 2 Peace or comfort in God and in conſcience.<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 119 71.61.</note> For <hi>marke the perfect man &amp; behold the iuſt the end of that man is peace.</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 37.37. 2 Cor. 4 17.</note> 3, <hi>Glory.</hi> for<note n="ſ" place="margin">Iam. 5.11.</note> 
                     <hi>our light affliction which is but for a moment work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for vs a farre more exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eternall weight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> The beginning and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of <hi>Iobs</hi> troubles, were very harſh and greeuous: but
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18937:22"/> 
                     <hi>S. Iames</hi> tells vs that<note n="t" place="margin">Ioh. 8.16</note> 
                     <hi>we haue ſeene and theard what an end God made.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is true the viſitation of the plague is vncomfortable, becauſe the feare of infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on makes friends afraide to ſee vs: but it is content that we haue had ſome that haue viſited vs; and it is comfort that though we had not had one to come vnto vs, yet had we not been alone, <hi>for</hi>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> 
                     <hi>God our Father hath beene with vs. <hi rend="sup">x</hi> he hath not forſaken vs in our bondage,</hi> for hee hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>neuer to leaue of, nor to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake any of his.</hi> And Ieſus Chriſt hath been with vs, for <hi rend="sup">y</hi> 
                     <hi>whereſoeuer two or three are gathered together, in the name of Chriſt, hee is in the midſt of them,</hi> and wee (according to our neede and dutie) haue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18937:23"/> often humbled our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in priuate faſting, praying, ſearching of our hearts, and confeſſing our ſinnes, which is (in part) to bee gathered together in the name of Chriſt. It was <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Riddle, that<note n="z" place="margin">Iudg. 14 14.</note> 
                     <hi>out of the eater ſhould come meate, and out of the ſtrong ſhould come ſweet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> And it is a Chriſtians Riddle, That out of affliction ſhould come conſolation: for of all the birds of the ayre fewe ſing in winter; but the <hi>Red-breſt.</hi> And of all the trees of the garden, few are greene but the Bay tree; and of all ſorts of men, few<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 5.3</note> 
                     <hi>reioyce in tribulation,</hi> but the godly.</p>
                  <p>That they haue cauſe to reioyce in tribulation, bath euen now ben ſhewed in fiue ſeuerall points. That they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18937:23"/> ought to doe ſo, wee are taught by the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Iames</hi> who wills Chriſtians<note n="b" place="margin">Iam. 1.2.</note> 
                     <hi>to account it exceeding ioy, when they fall into diuers tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</hi> That they do ſo may bee ſeene by the exampl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apoſtles, who<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 5.41 Col. 1.24</note> 
                     <hi>reioyced that they were counted worthy to ſuffer for Chriſt:</hi> how it comes to paſſe ſhall be ſhewed hereafter. In the mean while you that are made ſorrowfull with our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, bee ioyfull at our conſolation: and ſo from aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaging your griefe, I come to compound your feare. Your feare is twofold, partly in reſpect of vs, and partly alſo in reſpect of your ſelues.</p>
                  <p>Your fear in reſpect of vs, is, leaſt the hand of God ſhould ſtill bee ſtretched out
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18937:24"/> againſt our familie, to ſtrike more with the infection that is amongſt vs, and to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way more by death of it.</p>
                  <p>To hearten you againſt this feare,<note place="margin">How to hearten our ſelues againſt the feard of the plague.</note> I pray you to take into your thought and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion theſe three things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Though the Lord be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to proceed againſt vs ſtill, and though hee ſhould bee iuſt, if hee did ſo: yet it may pleaſe the Lord to ſpare vs<note n="d" place="margin">1. Sam. 12.22.</note> 
                     <hi>for his owne Names ſake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Ierem. 1.7.</note> 
                     <hi>it hath pleaſed the Lord to make vs his people:</hi> for the Lord<note n="f" place="margin">Eph. 3.20</note> 
                     <hi>is able to doe exceeding aboundantly aboue all that wee are able to aske or thinke.</hi> Hee deales not with his <hi>children according to their iniquities,</hi> for who ſhould remain in health or life?<note place="margin">Ahac. 3.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Euen in iudgement the Lord remembers mercy,</hi> as the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18937:24"/> Prophet <hi>Abacuck</hi> tells vs, &amp; as wee ſee it proued in that great plague in Iſrael, for when the Angel of the Lord had ſlaine thereof 70000 in three dayes;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24.19.</note> and hee began <hi>to ſtretch out his hand againſt Ieruſalem alſo, the Lord repented him of the euill, and ſaid to the Angel that had deſtroyed the people, It is enough, ſtay now thy hand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That all are not infected, or die not of the infection: It is not becauſe he is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to doe it, or if he did it, it were not iuſt, and all did not deſerue it:<note place="margin">Lament. 3.31.32.33.</note> but becauſe the <hi>Lord will not caſt off for euer, though hee cauſe griefe: yet will he haue compaſsion ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18937:25"/> his mercies for he doth not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict willingly;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mica. 7.18</note> for <hi>who is a God like vnto our God, that pardoneth iniquitie, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by the tranſgreſſion of the remnant of his heritage, he retaineth not his anger for euer, becauſe hee delighteth in mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Though the Lord ſhould ſmite vs all with the ſtroke of this ſickneſſe, ſo that wee were all infected and ſicke of it: (as in ſome families better then ours it is, &amp; as iuſtly hee may deale with vs for ought we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reſiſt, or can deſerue to the contrary) yet may it pleaſe God to ſpare vs that wee die not.<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſal. 38.1.5</note> 
                     <hi>Ezekiah</hi> was ſicke of the plague (as the learned iudge) and the text
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18937:25"/> ſaith, <hi>he was ſicke vnto death,</hi> (that is) in his owne appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and in the opinion of the Phyſicians, and in the violent and malignant na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the diſeaſe: yet did he recouer &amp; liued fifteene yeeres after. The like is to bee ſeene by daily experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of many that doe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine:<note n="b" place="margin">Ionah. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Ionah</hi> was in the ſea, but hee was not drowned:<note n="c" place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> The three children were in the fire, but were not burnt:<note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Daniel</hi> was in the den of Lions, but was not deuoured. And why may not we be kept from dying of the plague, though wee ſhould bee infected; with it (if the Lord be ſo pleaſed in his free fauour.) Seeing in generall afflictions,<note n="e" place="margin">Amos 4.11.</note> 
                     <hi>ſome
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18937:26"/> are as firebrands pluckt out of the burning:</hi> euen as in har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt ſom gleanings are ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered that are not gathered by the owner, and in the vintage ſome cluſters of grapes are left on the vine, that are not pluckt off.</p>
                  <p>I write not this in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as if I thought with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag,</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.32.</note> 
                     <hi>The bitterneſſe of death vvas paſt,</hi> or in preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if I were paſt all feare: the conſcience of mine own vnworthynes, &amp; the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods after recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings with ſom families do keepe mee from ſuch folly. But becauſe the ſeruants of God, may (with <hi>Abraham</hi>)<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 4.18.</note> 
                     <hi>hope againſt hope.</hi> We doe not confidently, aſſure our ſelues that it ſhall be ſo, but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18937:26"/> comfortably we hope it wil, in the free fauor and mercie of God, which is as great as is his Maieſtie, and <hi>vvho vvill haue mercy on them, on vvhom he vvill haue mercy.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Rom. 9.15.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. What though all in our family, that are now in health and life ſhould bee ſmitten, and that <hi>we</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Iſai 21.14</note> 
                     <hi>could not bee purged from our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie till vvee die:</hi> then for content, I ſay, for vs all (as <hi>Paul</hi> did for himſelf and his companions)<note n="k" place="margin">Act. 22.</note> 
                     <hi>The vvill of of the Lord be done.</hi> And as Chriſt our bleſſed Sauiour hath taught vs to ſay,<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 9.10</note> 
                     <hi>Thy vvill be done on earth as it is in heauen.</hi> More particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſay for my ſelfe, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did for himſelfe, <hi rend="sup">l</hi> 
                     <hi>Here am I,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.24.</note> let him doe to mee as ſeemeth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18937:27"/> good to him.</hi> And for my ſelfe, and children, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, I ſay, as good old <hi>Eli</hi> did for his ſonnes.<note n="m" place="margin">1 Sam. 3, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi> And for comfort to my ſelfe and you, I ſay,<note n="n" place="margin">Heb. 4 9.</note> 
                     <hi>There remaines a reſt for Gods people.</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 15 19.</note> 
                     <hi>We haue hope in Chriſt, not in this life onely:</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">1 Cor. 51</note> 
                     <hi>For vvee know that if our earthly houſe of this taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle be diſſolued, vvee haue a building of GOD, not made vvith handes, eternall in the heauens.</hi>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">2. Pet. 3 13.</note> 
                     <hi>We according to his promiſe look for new heauens, and a new earth, vvherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe.</hi> For <hi>we know that our Redeemer liueth.</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Iob. 19.25.</note> Wee <hi>know vvhom vvee haue truſted, and vvee are perſwaded that hee is able
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18937:27"/> to keepe that which wee haue committed vnto him againſt that day.</hi> And therefore<note n="s" place="margin">2. Tim 1.12.</note> 
                     <hi>though the Lord kill vs, yet will we truſt in him.</hi>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Iob 13.15.</note> And ſo I deſcend from your feare for vs, to your feare for your ſelues.</p>
                  <p>Your feare for your ſelues and your owne families is, that though hitherto the Lord hath ſpared your houſes from the viſitation: yet hereafter ere hee make an end he may, though not with the firſt, yet with the laſt, either ſoone, or Syne.</p>
                  <p>Concerning this your feare, I muſt firſt giue you ſome inſtructions 2. Some directions: And thirdly, ſome conſolations.</p>
                  <p>The Inſtructions ſhall be<note place="margin">How we may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully feare the Plague</note>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:18937:28"/> in two points. 1. How farre you may feare the plague lawfully. 2. How farre, and in what reſpects you may not feare the plague.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. You may lawfully feare the plague in three reſpects. 1. In reſpect of it ſelfe. 2. In reſpect of God. 3. In reſpect of your ſelues.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In reſpect of the plague it ſelfe, becauſe it <hi>is</hi>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">2 Chron. 20 9.</note> 
                     <hi>an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill</hi> of puniſhment: It is<note n="u" place="margin">1 Reg. 8.30</note> a <hi>plague or ſicknes, It is</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Deut. 28.21.</note> 
                     <hi>a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuming peſtilence.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a great plague, yea, one of the <hi>foure great plagues of God,</hi> with which hee ſcourges his people when they rebell againſt him,<note place="margin">Ezek. 44.21.</note> namely, The <hi>Famine, the Sword, wilde Beaſts, and Peſtilen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18937:28"/>2. In reſpect of God like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is to bee feared, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is <hi>his ſword</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he killeth: whoſoeuer is ſmitten with this ſicknes, hee is ſaid after an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner, and more immediately<note n="y" place="margin">Ezek. 14 21</note> 
                     <hi>to fall into the hands of God,</hi> which is <hi>a</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">1. Chron 24.12.</note> 
                     <hi>fearefull thing.</hi> When the Lord ſends this puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into a land, he is ſaid <hi>to</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam 24.14.</note> 
                     <hi>powre out his fury vpon it in blood,</hi> and to<note n="b" place="margin">Heq. 10.31.</note> 
                     <hi>plead with it in blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. In reſpect of your ſelues, you may warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly feare the plague for two cauſes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe you are but fleſh and blood, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſubiect to bee infected by the malignant qualitie
<pb facs="tcp:18937:29"/> of it, and to be corrupted in your blood with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of it. For you are not made of ſtones which it cannot pierce, yee are as weake as water, and cannot reſiſt the ſtroke of GODS Angel, you are<note n="b" place="margin">Ier. 18.6.</note> 
                     <hi>as clay</hi> and cannot reſiſt the Potter.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. You may feare the plague in reſpect of your ſelues: becauſe you are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and it is inflicted as a chaſtiſement for<note n="c" place="margin">1 King 8 33.37.</note> ſin. Wee haue beene partakers of the ſins of this Citie, that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved God to ſend it,<note place="margin">Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r. 28, 15.22. 2 Sam. 24 17.</note> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may iuſtly feare we ſhall be partakers in the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation of the Citie by the plague ſooner or later, by infection, or by death, wee our ſelues, or ours. We that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18937:29"/> haue deſerued the worſt, may war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>antably feare the worſt; though God ſhould be pleaſed beyond our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation &amp; deſert, <hi>to ſpare vs as a</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Mal. 3.17</note> 
                     <hi>father doth his own child which ſerueth him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">How you may not feare the plague.</note> You may not lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare the plague in other reſpects, as namely, 1. Not fooliſhly. 2. Not profanely. 3. Not deſperately.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. You may not feare the plague fooliſhly or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhly out of a fond conceit, That if you come neere a perſon, or houſe infected, you muſt preſently receiue the contagion of it. The plague is but <hi>GODS</hi> crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whether it ſtrike vs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by an Angel, or mediately by infection fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18937:30"/> men; therfore can he coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termand it, when hee will. That he doth countermand his Angel, that is ſent to deſtroy of this diſeaſe is plain; where the Lord ſaith,<note n="e" place="margin">2 Sam. 24 16</note> 
                     <hi>Stay thy hand, it is enough:</hi> and that hee can and doth reſtraine the power of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection that is in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, it is euident by thoſe which viſit them (as Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians and Surgeons) and by thoſe which keep them that are ſicke of it, (as Nurſes &amp; Keepers) that ſweat them and dreſſe their ſores, and waſh their linnen that coms from them, polluted with the filthy corruption that comes out of their ſores, yea which lie with them that haue ſores running on
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18937:30"/> them, and are continually in their breath, and drinke after them in the ſame cup, who notwithſtanding are preſerued from touch of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
                  <p>I ſuppoſe it comes to paſs, not becauſe the plague is not in it ſelfe infectious, (as ſome ignorantly &amp; ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſly haue thought and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) but it is effected by an extraordinary hand of God by his wiſdome and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne power, and namely, and of purpoſe to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage people to bee pittifull to them that are diſeaſed with it, &amp; to hearten them in this deed of charitie to miniſter to them: for the Lord knowes that without tending of them that are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18937:31"/> thus viſited, many would pinch miſerably, and if all ſhould be infected that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e neere them that were viſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, there would be few or none to tend them.</p>
                  <p>Is not the fire of a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning nature in it ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome one houſe in a ſtreete, or one roume in a houſe eſcaps burning, by the wiſe and powerfull pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vidence of God; when the reſt are burnt to aſhes. Even ſo, the plague it ſelfe, is in it owne nature malignant &amp; infectious, &amp; (yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the malignancy of it) the Lord can and doth reſtraine it, and therefore it is not to be feared fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if God could not keep vs if wee came neere where
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18937:31"/> it is, but we muſt needes be infected by it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 You muſt not feare the Plague profanely, which they do that more feare the puniſhing Angell the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, and the infection of it, more then to ſinne; as they doe that in this time of con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tagion runne away from the Citie, and carry their ſinnes with them into the Countrey, namely, their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie and impenitencie, their pride &amp; covetouſnes, whereby it comes to paſſe, that they neither repent of their owne ſinnes, nor bee greived for <hi>the affliction of Ioſeph,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos 6.6.</note> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſerate their brethren in miſery.</p>
                  <p>I ſpeake not of all that depart, for ſome doe it war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantab y
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18937:32"/> in a godly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, without diffidence in God for themſelues, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their afflicted brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; but of ſuch as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt their impenitency, by going on in their former ſinnes, and ſpending this heauie time in paſtime and merriment, and ſhew their vnmercifulneſſe by leauing nothing behind them for the poore and ſicke when they went, nor haue ſent no thing to them ſince they went, nor haue a purpoſe to doe it, when they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne. Thus wee may not feare the plague,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.28</note> for wee muſt not feare them which <hi>can but kill the body, and can do no more,</hi> but <hi>we muſt feare him &amp; it, which can kill both
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18937:32"/> ſoule and body</hi> (that is) <hi>God and Sinne.</hi> The plague can but infect the blood, and thereby fill the body with putrified ſores, that it die. But ſin can kill both ſoule and body too, and therfore wee ought not ſo much to feare the plague, as we doe to offend God.</p>
                  <p>Wee ought not to pray ſo to bee kept from the plague, as to be kept from ſinne: we ought not to bee thankful ſo much for being kept from the plague, as from ſin, nor ought wee to bee ſo watchfull ouer our ſelues, that wee bee not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the plague, as that wee be not corrupted by the deceitfulneſſe of ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; for the one is ſimply euill,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18937:33"/> ſo is not the other at all: the one is a breach of GODS Law; the other is but a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of that breach.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. You muſt not feare the plague deſperately, ſo as to thinke that if you bee ſmitten with it, and die of it, That preſently therefore you are none of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and that you ſhall not die in Gods fauour (as ſome ſottiſhly and blaſphemouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue giuen out.<note place="margin">Dan. 3.23.</note>)</p>
                  <p>With this point, becauſe I haue occaſion anon to meet, and to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>proue it, therefore I will referre it to its proper place, in the laſt generall point concerning your feare, which is the conſolations.</p>
                  <p>It is true, the ſtroke of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18937:33"/> plague is a ſigne of Gods temporall anger, but not of his eternall diſpleaſure. 1. Becauſe it is inflicted but on the bodie onely, and not on the ſoule. 2. Becauſe it is in this life onely infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and not in the life to come, and therefore by it ſelfe (without ſpirituall iudgements) of blindneſſe of minde, hardnes of heart and impenitencie,) it is no ſigne of Gods eternall wrath, becauſe a <hi>all things come a like to all, there is one euent to the righteous and to the wicked,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccle. 6.2</note> 
                     <hi>no man knoweth either loue or hatred, by all that is before thee,</hi> of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and worldly bleſſings, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> puniſhments, accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:18937:34"/>
                  <p>It is true, that in ſome fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milyes, God ſtriks all with ſickneſſe, in others none at a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l, Some infected perſons are very ſicke, others ayle nothing at all. This comes not to paſſe by chance, but by Gods Soveraigne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. If he pleaſe, hee can arme his cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tures ſo, as to kill whole houſholds, as he armed the fire to burne &amp; <hi>ſlay thoſe men that tooke vp the three children,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 3.23.</note> 
                     <hi>and putt them into the firy Fornace,</hi> therfore you ſhould feare it as I haue formerly ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght you to doe, and as warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablie you may. Againe, he can reſtraine and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his creature, ſo as not to kill one in a Familie though they be all infect<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18937:34"/> no, nor in in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ect any one, no, nor to make any one ill at eaſe of it, though they be infected, as hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained the heate of that exceeding whott fier, that it <hi>had no power one their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan 3.27.</note> 
                     <hi>an hayre of their heads was not ſindged, neither were their coates changed, nor had the ſmell of fire</hi> paſſed one them, therefore you ſhould not feare it as ſome doe, (whereof you haue heard before) vnwarrantably.</p>
                  <p>If euery one ſhould die that were infected, ſome would ſay, God were not able to keepe aliue him that were ſmitten with the plague: and if none ſhould die of it, many would ſet light by it, and not humble
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18937:35"/> themſelues before GOD when they are ſmitten with it. Let vs therefore in theſe two reſpects in this morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, walke before GOD with Feare &amp; Faith. With Feare, becauſe by ſin we are ſubiect to the infection: for it is iuſt with God, that we who doe corrupt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſoules with the eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll example of our words and workes vnto ſin, ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo infect one anothers bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies with the contagion of this diſeaſe vnto puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and let vs walke with Faith, becauſe he can coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termaund and reſtraine it. And thus much for my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions concerning your feare of the plague, namely, how farre you may feare it,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18937:35"/> and how far you may not. The directions concerning this your feare doe follow.</p>
                  <p>My directions touching your feare of the plague, ſhall be giuen in two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. 1. I will direct you how you may preſerue your ſelues from being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the plague. 2. I will direct you how you may keep your ſelues from dying of the plague, thogh you be infected with it: &amp; this wil I do, not as a friend, by requeſting you to bee wary into what houſe or company you come (which I need not doe.) Nor as a Phyſician, by preſcribing vnto you ſome rare preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiues (which I cannot do) but as a Miniſter and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18937:36"/> of the Goſpel, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing you ſome good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel from the Word of God, which (being followed) wil (by Gods bleſſing) bee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for theſe endes, (if the Lord ſee it good for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and our ſaluation) then all the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rs</hi> ſtone, Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corns horne, or Mith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idate in the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Sixe meanes to preu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt the infecti n of the plagu</note>For the firſt. The means to preuent the plague are in number ſix, and they are of two kindes. 1. Such as concerne God. 2. Such as concerne our ſelues.</p>
                  <p>The meanes which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne God are three.</p>
                  <p>The firſt meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the plague which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes God is Faith, (that is) truſt or confidence in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18937:36"/> God, whereby we reſt and rely on his power &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for protection, and not on the broken reeds of any outward meanes, as good ayre, refraining company, ſhift of roomes, and varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of perfumes, much leſſe on any exorciſed preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues &amp; enchanted Tablets, or Amul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts to weare about our necks for that end.</p>
                  <p>To truſt in God, <hi>In whom we liue, moue,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act 17.28</note> 
                     <hi>and haue our being,</hi> is to make <hi>him our rocke and our ſortreſſe.</hi> And becauſe <hi>the righteous man makes the Lord his refuge, and the moſt high his habitation, therefore there ſhal none euill befall him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 91.9.10.11.</note> 
                     <hi>neither ſhall the plague come nigh his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, for he ſhall giue his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18937:37"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18937:37"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:18937:38"/> charge ouer him to keepe him in all his wayes.</hi> For by this faith or relying on God, the Iſraelites, when they had no power in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ouercame their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the Hagarites, and for want of this faith,<note place="margin">1 Chro. 5.20.</note> or <hi>truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in God</hi> his wrath fell vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>78.21</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond means which concernes God, is <hi>ſeeking his face and fauor,</hi> his mercy and his loue, wherby his anger may be appeaſed towardes vs, and his diſpleaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, which prouokes him to ſend his peſtilence among vs.</p>
                  <p>To this <hi>ſeeking of Gods face,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Chron. 7.14.</note> wee are directed by the Spirit of God in the Word, and vnto this is promiſed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18937:38"/> likewiſe a bleſſing. For to haue the <hi>Lord to lift vp the light of his countenance vpon vs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.8.</note> is better then all the contents of worldlings, yea better <hi>then life it ſelfe.</hi> The Lord ſaith to vs, <hi>ſeeke yee my face,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 27, 8.</note> and wee muſt ſay to to him, <hi>Thy face Lord wil we ſeeke,</hi> yea wee muſt ſeeke it before health or life. For if we enioy his fauour we are happy, though we were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected vnto death; and if we want this, we are accurſed, though wee ſhould neuer bee ſmitten or die of the plague.</p>
                  <p>The third meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the plague,<note place="margin">The third</note> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes God, is feruent and faithfull prayer to God in the name of Chriſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18937:39"/> to his will.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2. Chron. 7.14.</note>This is likewiſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Word, for this end; and to this is annexed a promiſe to encourage vs to the practiſe thereof.</p>
                  <p>By praier <hi>Moſes</hi> preuent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the plague fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falling ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally on all the Iſraelites, when <hi>ſome of them dyed by the plague before the Lord.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Numb. 14.20.37.38. 1. Cor. 10.10.</note> And by prayer <hi>Moſes</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted another great plague and vtter deſtruction from falling on the Iſraelites, &amp; did therby (as it were) bind the hands of the Lord that hee could not ſmite them:<note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> for the Lord ſaid,<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.11</note> 
                     <hi>Let me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone that my wrath may waxe hot againſt them, and that I may conſume them.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 14</note> And vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this prayer the <hi>Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18937:39"/> him of the euill which hee thought to doe vnto his people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The meanes which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our ſelues, and which are good to preuent the plague from ſmiting vs, are likewiſe three: but they are of two ſorts. 1. Some which concerne our ſins, and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. 2. Some which concernes our dutie and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe which concerne our ſins are two.</p>
                  <p>The firſt meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the plague which concernes our ſelues and our ſinnes,<note place="margin">The fourth.</note> is humbling our ſelues in ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy before the Lord in a free confeſſion of our ſins, and acknowledgement of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18937:40"/> our worthineſſe to be ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by it.</p>
                  <p>This humiliation was commaunded by the Lord to the people of Iſrael, and conſequently to vs in them in the like caſe,<note place="margin">2 Chr. 7.14</note> and to it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is promiſed a bleſſing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1 Chro. 21 15.16.17. 2 Sam. 24.17.</note>This <hi>Dauid and the Elders of Iſrael did, being clothed in ſackcloth and falling on their faces.</hi> And by this they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented the ſtroke of the Angel, when <hi>hee ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the earth and heauen, hauing a drawne ſword in his hand ſtretched out ouer Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> namely, to deſtroy it alſo by the plague, as other parts of the Countrey had euen then beene.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Amo 4.22.</note>By this humiliation wee <hi>meet God</hi> to pacifie his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18937:40"/> (as <hi>Iacob</hi> did his brother <hi>Eſau</hi>) and by this wee <hi>hide our ſelues</hi> from the puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing hand of God,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 22.3.</note> when we ſee it comming towards vs. By this <hi>Ioſiah</hi> and the <hi>Niniuites</hi> preuented the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of GODS iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments threatned.<note place="margin">1 Chro. 34.28. Ionah. 3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond means which concernes our ſins,<note place="margin">The fift.</note> and is effectual for the preuenting of the plague, is zeale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſin in our ſelues and others, <hi>for God and his ſake.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Num. 25.11.12.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>This zeale againſt ſin, is to be ſhewed by vs, either as Magiſtrates vpon Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors (notorious ones e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially:<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.30</note>) for by this <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias ſtayed the plague,</hi> when foure &amp; twentie thouſand had dyed thereof. Or as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18937:41"/> Miniſters or Maſters of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, by rebuking &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting ſin in our people, ſeruants and children. Or as Chriſtians,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31. 2 cor. 7.11</note> by <hi>iudging our ſelues,</hi> &amp; taking <hi>reuenge on our ſelues.</hi> And this wee doe when wee deny to our ſinfull ſenſes, the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and contents of ſin, (which is <hi>to plucke out the right eye,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 23.19</note> and to <hi>cut off our right hand, and to caſt it from vs</hi>) and when we <hi>beat down the body of ſin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. cor. 9.27</note> by faſting and temperance. And this is a meanes to keep vs from <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing iudged of the Lord.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11 32.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſixt<note place="margin">The Sixt</note> and laſt meanes to keep vs from the infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the plague, concernes our duty and obedience to God, and it is faithfulneſſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18937:41"/> and diligence in our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, with prudence to keepe vs within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of our own waies: for the Lord hath promiſed, that hee <hi>will giue his Angels charge ouer his children to keepe them in all their wayes.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 91.11.</note> And this <hi>Ezekiah</hi> found; for hee walked before the Lord in truth and vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not onely as an Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite or Chriſtian; but as a King and Gouernour, and hereby hee was preſerued. For (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>Hee that walkes vprightly,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 28.18</note> 
                     <hi>walkes ſafely.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the ſecond:<note place="margin">Six meanes to keepe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dying of the plague.</note> The meanes to remooue the plague, and to keepe you from dying of it, though you be infected with it, are
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18937:42"/> likewiſe ſix, and they are of two ſorts. 1. Ciuill. 2. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The firſt.</note>The Ciuill meanes is the vſing of skilfull &amp; religious Phyſicians and Surgeons, in obedience to Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and with truſt in his power and bleſſing. For by the commandement of the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord, <hi>Ezekiah</hi> was to take <hi>a lumpe of dry figs,</hi> and <hi>to lay it on the ſore,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Reg. 20.7.</note> and by this meanes (through Gods bleſſing) <hi>hee did recouer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Religious means to keepe vs from dying of the plague, are fiue; and they be of two kinds: for they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne either God, or our ſelues.</p>
                  <p>The meanes which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18937:42"/> GOD are two.</p>
                  <p>The firſt meanes to keep vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dying of the plague and which concernes God,<note place="margin">The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</note> is earneſt and fervent pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yer to God to keepe vs a liue, either by his bleſſing on the meanes if we haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or without, if wee haue none.</p>
                  <p>By prayer,<note place="margin">Num. 16.46.47.48.</note> the <hi>plague was ſtayed in Iſraell,</hi> when it <hi>was begun</hi> very hot. For incenſe was offered vp with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God, &amp; the offering vp of incenſe Ceremonial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did ſignifie &amp; teach the putting vp, and accepting of our feruent prayers, as is playne by the Pſalmiſt, where he ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 141.2.</note> 
                     <hi>let my prayer be ſet forth before thee as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe and the lifting vp of my
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18937:43"/> hands, bee, as the euening Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</hi> And of this <hi>Ezekiah</hi> had good experience when the Lord ſaid, <hi>I haue heard thy prayer &amp; ſeene thy teares,</hi> behold <hi>I will add vnto thy dayes fifteene</hi> years.<note place="margin">Iſay 38.5.</note> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,<note place="margin">2 chr. 6.29 1 Reg. 8.37.38.</note> the Lord promiſed to heare their prayer made by the Iſraelits when they were viſited by the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and the Lord hath promiſed Chriſtians, that thy <hi>prayer of faith ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the ſicke.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 1.15.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The third</note>The Second meanes which concernes God and that will keepe vs from dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the plague, is zeale and forwardnes in erecting and eſtabliſhing (and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently in deuout and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious frequenting &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming)
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18937:43"/> of the pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, according to his Word and Will.</p>
                  <p>We read that when God was about to ſtay his hand from ſlaying the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by the plague, that the Lord (as a meanes thereunto) bids his Angel to commaund his Prophet <hi>Gad</hi> to ſay to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Goe vp,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Chron. 21.18.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſet vp an Altar to the Lord in the thre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhing floore of Araunah the Iebuſite:</hi> Whereunto <hi>Dauid</hi> obeying, the text ſaith, that <hi>hee went vp at the ſaying of Gad,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſe 19.</note> 
                     <hi>which hee ſpake in the name of the Lord: Then Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſaid to Ornan grant mee the place of this threſhing floore,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſe 22.</note> 
                     <hi>that I may build an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar thereon vnto the Lord
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18937:44"/> (thou ſhalt grant it me for the full price) that the plague may be ſtaied from the people.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Note 1 Sam. 24.</note> And when <hi>Dauid</hi> had bought &amp; paid for it,<note place="margin">Verſe 26.</note> then the Text ſaith, <hi>Dauid built there an Altar to the Lord, and offered burnt offerings and peace offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, and called vpon the Lord.</hi> And to the end it might appeare, he accepted this worſhip for the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his wrath, and ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the plague: The <hi>Lord anſwered him from heauen by fier vpon the Altar of burnt offerings.</hi> For in the very next Verſe it is ſaid,<note place="margin">verſ. 37.</note> that the <hi>Lord commanded the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                     <hi>and he put vp his ſword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into the ſheath thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee reade alſo, that the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:18937:44"/> made this a reaſon to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade <hi>Pharaoh to let them go three dayes iourney,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 5.3.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Lord their God,</hi> leaſt (ſay they) <hi>hee fall vpon vs with the peſtilence.</hi> Which ſhewes, that if neglecting Gods worſhip be a meanes to bring the plague: then zeale and deuotion in erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, countenancing, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of Gods worſhip according to his will is a meanes to remoue it, and to keepe vs from dying of it. And we may very probably coniecture, not without good warrant that the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne worſhip of GOD, with faſting, praying, and preaching, appointed by Authoritie, hath beene a meanes (not for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18937:45"/> of it: but by Gods bleſſing on his owne Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance) to ſtay the ſickneſſe, and to abate the multitudes that died thereof.</p>
                  <p>The meanes to preuent death of the plague which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cern our ſelues, are three.</p>
                  <p>The firſt appertains to the iudgement of the plague it ſelfe,<note place="margin">The fourth.</note> and it is a ſenſible fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling when wee are ſmitten with it in our own ſoules of the heauy hand of God, by laying it cloſe to our harts. Which we do when we are made to ſearch out our ſins which are the cauſe therof, and when we conſider ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly of Gods heauy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure therein againſt our ſinnes:<note place="margin">1 Reg. 8.37, 38. 2 Chron. 6.28, 29.</note> for to this is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed a bleſſing, &amp; indeed
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18937:45"/> this will make vs pray hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly &amp; feruently for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of our ſinnes, the cauſe therof that they being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, a way may be made for mercy vnto vs. And S. <hi>Peter</hi> tels vs,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.6.</note> that <hi>if we hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelues vnder the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hand of God, hee will exalt vs in due time.</hi> And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.16.</note> that the <hi>prayer of the righteous man preuaileth much with God, if it be feruent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond means which concernes our ſelues,<note place="margin">The fift.</note> and is good to keepe vs from dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the plague belongs to our ſinnes, and it is a tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from them &amp; leauing them. For when Gods <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Chron. 7.13, 14.</note> 
                     <hi>on whom his Name is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſhal turne from their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18937:46"/> wayes,</hi> he hath promiſed <hi>to heale them of the peſtilence.</hi> For by this wee cauſe God <hi>to repent of the euill.</hi> And by this we remooue and <hi>put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the euill of our doing</hi> from before the eye of the Lord which were the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of it,<note place="margin">Ionah. 3.10</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 1.16.</note> &amp; puniſh our ſelues for our ſin, that we may not be puniſhed of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The ſixt.</note>The third means which concernes our ſelues, and is auailable to preuent our death of the plague apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God, and it is ſincerity &amp; vprightnes of heart, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we deſire and endeuour to walke in obedience to all Gods commandements, in the refraining of all known ſinnes (euen our beloued
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18937:46"/> ones) and in the practiſing of all knowne duties, cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, conſcionably, and conſtantly.</p>
                  <p>The Lord tells vs by the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 14.17, 20.</note> that the <hi>righteous ſhall by his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe deliuer his owne life from the peſtilence,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 10.2.</note> and <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith that <hi>Righteouſneſſe deliuers from death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An experiment of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignty of this meanes &amp; medicine wee haue in <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> who to preuent (if it were poſſible) his death of this ſickneſſe with which he was ſmitten (as the learned iudge) hee vſeth no better an argument to perſwade the Lord to heare him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in then this,<note place="margin">Iſay 38.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Remember mee now (O Lord) how I haue wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18937:47"/> before thee in truth and with a perfect heart, &amp; haue done that which is good in thy ſight,</hi> and behold what the Lord ſaid vnto him by his Prophet <hi>Iſai.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Reg. 20.6.</note> 
                     <hi>I haue added to thy dayes fifteene yeares, &amp; I will heale thee,</hi> and the <hi>third day thou ſhalt goe vp to the houſe of the Lord.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> And according to this promiſe, was Gods performance, for the text ſaith plainely,<note place="margin">Verſe 7.</note> that <hi>he recouered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Cautions touching the efficacy of theſe meanes to keepe vs from infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or death of the plague.</note>But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning theſe dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, I muſt giue you ſom cautions, to teach you how for you are to rely on them for the preventing of infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the plague, or death by infection.</p>
                  <p>You are to know then: 1. That you are not to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18937:47"/> think to prevaile with God to theſe endes, by vſing ſome one of theſe meanes that is eaſieſt to be done, or which you like to chooſe: but by the vſing of them all with continuance therein. 2. You are not to expect preſervatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, howeuer they be performed by you, but then, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for manner, aſwel as for matter they are done according to the Word.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. You are not to imagine that you can me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite preſeruation by theſe meanes, for when you doe them beſt,<note n="h" place="margin">Lu. 17.10</note> 
                     <hi>you are vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſeruants:</hi> for the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie of theſe exerciſes to their ſeueral ends, depends not on our good perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: but on Gods inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18937:48"/> and bleſſing.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. You muſt not look to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by theſe religious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes preſeruation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or death, abſolutly, but with condition and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation only. For we muſt vſe theſe meanes in faith &amp; beleife to receiue good by them, elſe why doe wee vſe them as Gods ordinances to this end? and wee muſt by faith beleeue to receiue good by them, ſo farre as God meanes and intends we ſhall, (for it is in vayne to looke for it otherwiſe) and God meanes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends we ſhall receiue good by theſe holy exerciſes, ſo farr as he hath reuealed his will and meaning, for thus ſpeaks the Scripture which
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18937:48"/> reveals Gods will and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning herein,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.14</note> If <hi>wee aske any thing according to Gods will, he heareth vs.</hi> And <hi>the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit maketh interceſsion for the Saints according to the will of GOD.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.27</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But you will aske me, what is this will of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which wee are to pray? and what is asked according to Gods will? Surely, that which God doth will and meane to grant. What doth God will &amp; meane to grant? Surely that which he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to giue. What is that which God hath promiſed to giue? Surely, good things: for ſo ſpeakes the Scripture,<note n="l" place="margin">Mat 7.11</note> 
                     <hi>Your Father which is in heauen will giue
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18937:49"/> good things to them that aske him.</hi> They <hi>which</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 34.9 10.</note> 
                     <hi>feare the Lord ſtall want nothing that is good.</hi> And no <hi>good</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Pſ. 84.11</note> 
                     <hi>thing will hee with hold from them that liue vprightly.</hi> And what be thoſe good things? Surely thoſe which are good for Gods glory and good for our ſaluation. For what doth God will more then his own glory, and the ſaluation of his Elect? See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee hath appointed their ſaluation by his own Sonne,<note place="margin">Eph. 1.5.6.11.12.</note> 
                     <hi>according to the good pleaſure of his will, for the praiſe of the glory of his grace wherein hee hath made vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted in the beloued.</hi> What is good, if theſe bee not: what is good without theſe? Is it not enough for
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18937:49"/> vs poore ſinners, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue not our health or life vpon any conditions, to in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioy them vpon theſe terms; but wee muſt haue them without Gods good will, &amp; whether or no it bee good for Gods glory &amp; our own ſaluation, or elſe we are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, and God is not true of his word, nor carefull of vs? Far be ſuch ſtrange luſt from Chriſtians (whoſe lot is the Lord, and whoſe por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is heauen) to deſire to liue here to the diſhonour of God, and the hinderance of their owne ſaluation; far be it from crauers to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and beggars chooſers. And ſo I come to the third thing which I propounded to deliuer touching your
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18937:50"/> feare, and it is comfort and conſolation.</p>
                  <p>The comfort is againſt your feare to die of the plague: and it is this. That though you die of it, yet are you not accurſed: but you ſhal die in the loue and fauour of God, for you ſhal <hi>die</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Num. 23, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>the death of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:</hi> you ſhall<note n="p" place="margin">Reu. 14.13.</note> 
                     <hi>reſt from your labours:</hi> yee ſhall<note n="q" place="margin">Lu. 2.27. 1 Theſ. 4.14.</note> 
                     <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in peace,</hi> and <hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>ſleepe in Ieſus;</hi> which whoſoeuer doth is bleſſed.</p>
                  <p>In handling this matter of comfort, I will obſerue this method.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I will proue that the fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thfull doe die in Gods loue, though they die of the plague. 2. I will ſhew how it comes about to bee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18937:50"/> ſo. 3. I will giue you ſome Rules, by which you may aſſure your ſelues that you ſhall die in GODS loue, though you die of the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the godly die in the fauour of God, though they die of the plague, I wil proue by two Reaſons: of which this is the firſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> The faithfull that die of the plague, doe die in Gods loue; becauſe their death works to them ſpiritual and eternall good.</p>
                  <p>The Reaſon is good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing works to the ſpirituall and eternall good of the wicked, that doe not die in Gods loue: for they haue right to no ſpirituall or eternall good thing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18937:51"/> out of Chriſt,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Phi. 3.19</note> 
                     <hi>minding earthly things,</hi> and hauing <hi>their</hi>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 17.14</note> 
                     <hi>portion in this life</hi> onely.</p>
                  <p>And that the death of the godly, though it bee of the ſickneſſe, workes vnto their ſpiritual and eternall good; I proue by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes, That <hi>all</hi>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">Ro. 8.28</note> 
                     <hi>things worke together vnto good, to them that loue God, who are called according to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi> Whence I thus argue: If the death of the godly by the plague be ſomthing; then muſt it worke to the good of them, for all things work: &amp; if vnto their good, then vnto their ſpirituall and eternall good. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not likely that death ſhould worke vnto
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18937:51"/> any temporall good: for all temporal good things leaue them when they die. And ſecondly, becauſe the good, which by the text is ſaid to be wrought, is good vnto them <hi>that loue God,</hi> and are called <hi>of his purpoſe:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a ſpirituall and an eternall good, in the eternal loue of God to their ſoules.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> The godly, which die of the plague, doe dy in Gods loue: becauſe nothing can ſeparate them from the loue of God in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>The Reaſon is good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they that are ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the loue of God in Chriſt, doe die in Gods eternall diſpleaſure, becauſe they die in their ſinnes, and goe to hell. For if they that
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18937:52"/> 
                     <hi>dye in the Lord are</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Reu. 14.13.</note> 
                     <hi>bleſſed,</hi> then they that die out of him are accurſed.</p>
                  <p>And that the godly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſeparated from the loue of God in Chriſt, is plaine by the Apoſtle, who ſaith of himſelfe (and that which is true of one that is truely godly, is true of all that partake of the<note n="y" place="margin">Iude v. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaluation.) Neither</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Ro. 8.38.</note> 
                     <hi>life nor death, nor any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, can bee able to ſeparate me from the loue of God, which is in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Whence I thus reaſon. 1. If death cannot ſeparate the godly from the loue of <hi>God,</hi> then no death can: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite propoſitions are generall, &amp;, if no death can, then death of the plague
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18937:52"/> cannot. 2. If nothing can ſeparate the godly from his loue, then death of the plague cannot, for that is ſomething; and if death of the plague cannot ſeparate the faithfull from <hi>Gods</hi> loue in Chriſt: then muſt they needs dy in his loue, thogh they die of the plague. For<note n="a" place="margin">Ro. 14.8.</note> 
                     <hi>whether they liue, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they die, they are the Lords,</hi> &amp; therefore the Lord is theirs. The ſtate of <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> when hee lay full of ſores, and pouertie was (in the eye of the world) very wretched, yet was hee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his death: for hee <hi rend="sup">b</hi> 
                     <hi>was carried to Abrahams boſome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc 16.22.</note> and therefore died in Gods loue. Indeed death of the plague may ſeeme to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18937:53"/> ſeparate the godly from the loue of God: but it is a ſeparation of them from his loue of them, as his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures onely, not as his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, becauſe it is not a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of them from his <hi>loue of them</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 8.38.39.</note> 
                     <hi>in Chriſt.</hi> Death of the plague, is a ſigne of Gods diſpleaſure: but it is a ſigne of his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary diſpleaſure only, and not of his eternall. For though God, <hi>in</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 58.7, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>a little wrath hide himſelfe from his</hi> children, <hi>for a moment, yet with euerlaſting kindnes will hee haue mercie on them.</hi> Though God, by death of the plague take our life and health from vs:<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 89.31, 32.</note> Yet <hi>will he not take his louing kindnes from vs vtterly.</hi> Though
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18937:53"/> our friends depart from vs, and death of this ſickneſſe part the parents from the children, &amp;c. Yet<note n="f" place="margin">2. Sa. 7.15</note> 
                     <hi>Gods mercy ſhall not depart from vs.</hi> And ſo much of the firſt point, in the doctrine of comfort, touching your feare to die of the plague.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond point here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is to ſhew how it comes to paſſe, that the faithfull dy in Gods fauour though they dy of the plague.</p>
                  <p>This is effected by that which hath ben done,<note place="margin">How it coms to paſſe, that though the godly dy of the plague, they dy in Gods fauour.</note> and ſuffered, by our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt, in whoſe righteouſneſſe we<note n="g" place="margin">Eph. 1.6.</note> 
                     <hi>are accepted</hi> and by <hi>whoſe</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 53.5.</note> 
                     <hi>ſtripes we are healed.</hi> For 1. He <hi>hath</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Ioh. 16.33.</note> 
                     <hi>ouercome the world</hi> (that is) the afflictions of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18937:54"/> it, (one whereof is death) which the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world lay one them, ſo that the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions which his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren endure in this world, while they liue here cannot hinder their ſaluation in an other world. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this reſpect our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour wills them <hi>to be of good comfort,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Chriſt hath <hi>giuen</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 15 56.57.</note> 
                     <hi>vs victory ouer the ſtinge of death:</hi> that it cannot now bee vnto vs a paſſage to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death and damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as by nature through ſinne it was, and is to them that beleeue not in Chriſt, nor amend their liues. 3 Chriſt hath<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 2.14</note> 
                     <hi>ouercome him that had the power of death
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18937:54"/> which is the Deuill, by his owne death,</hi> ſo that he cannot car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie our ſoules to hell when we dy,<note place="margin">Luc. 16.22.</note> as he did the ſoule of <hi>Diues,</hi> and as he hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to execute that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on all thoſe that are out of Chriſt. 4. Chriſt <hi>hath</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> 
                     <hi>redeemed vs from the curſe of the law, being made a curſe for vs.</hi> And thereby freed vs from the curſe of any kind of death or afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bodily whatſoeuer. In which reſpect, S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith that <hi>in</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 8.35.36.37.</note> 
                     <hi>tribulation, in death in perſecution, in famine, in nakednes, in perill, in ſword,</hi> (and why not then <hi>in</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">1. Chron. 11.12.</note> 
                     <hi>the ſword of the Lord, euen the peſtilence) in all theſe things wee are more then Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, through him that hath
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:18937:55"/> loued vs,</hi> the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. cor. 1.30</note> 
                     <hi>vvho is made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs of God, wiſedome, righteouſnes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 2.21.</note> 
                     <hi>ſanctification, and redemption,</hi> and <hi>both in life and death advantage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">What makes death bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note>It is not the kind of death in reſpect of the matter, that makes men bleſſed or accurſſed: For in this reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect<note n="a" place="margin">Ezek. 9.2</note> 
                     <hi>all things comes a like to all there is one euent to the righteous and to the wicked. By this no man knoweth ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loue or hatred.</hi> But it is their graces, or their ſinnes, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch they carrie with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eir deathes, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or puniſhment that followes after them when they are dead, that makes them happy or miſerable.</p>
                  <p>The godly carrie their
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18937:55"/> graces &amp; vertues with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to death,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.13</note> for they <hi rend="sup">b</hi> 
                     <hi>dy in faith,</hi> they<note n="c" place="margin">Reuel. 14.13.</note> 
                     <hi>dy in the Lord,</hi> they<note n="d" place="margin">Lu. 2.29.</note> 
                     <hi>depart in peace.</hi> But the wicked carry their ſins to their death.<note n="e" place="margin">Iohn 8.21.24.</note> For <hi>they dy in their ſinnes,</hi> as <hi>Abſolon</hi> in his treaſon,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18. Num. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>Corah</hi> in his rebellion, and <hi>Herod</hi> in his pride, Act. 12.</p>
                  <p>That which followes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the godly, is heauen, for<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 4.9</note> 
                     <hi>there remaines a reſt for them,</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.5</note> 
                     <hi>an inheritance and incorruptible reſerued for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in heauen, Lazarus</hi> went to <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, and the good Theife on the Croſſe, was with <hi>Chriſt in Paradiſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 23.43</note> that very day he dyed. But that which follows the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked after their<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 9.27</note> 
                     <hi>death is iudgement,</hi> which is<note n="i" place="margin">Reu. 6.8.</note> 
                     <hi>hell
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18937:56"/> that followes death,</hi> &amp;<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 2.5</note> 
                     <hi>wrath againſt the day of wrath.</hi> As <hi>Iudas</hi> that went to<note n="l" place="margin">Act. 2.15.</note> 
                     <hi>his owne place,</hi> and <hi>Diues</hi> to<note n="m" place="margin">Luc. 16.22.</note> 
                     <hi>Hell</hi> when they died.</p>
                  <p>So that as long as yee dy not in your ſinnes nor goe to hell, but liue and dye in the grace of God and goe to heauen, which you ſhall certainely doe, if you liue and dye in Gods feare and in the faith of Chriſt, you muſt needes dye in Gods loue though yee dye of the plague.</p>
                  <p>The third and laſt point in the doctrine of comfort,<note place="margin">Rules to know how chriſtians ſhall dy in Gods fauour though they dy of the plague.</note> againſt the feare to dye of the plague, is to giue you ſome Rules, by which you may aſſure your ſelues, you ſhall dye, in the loue
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:18937:56"/> of God, and his eternall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, though you dye of the plague. To which I now addreſſe my ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>That you may aſſure your ſelues you ſhall dye in Gods loue, It is requiſite that firſt you bee ſure you liue in Gods loue. (for he cannot dye in any ſenſe that neuer liued in the ſame.) And that you may knowe you liue in Gods loue, it muſt appeare vnto you by the effects, and motions of this life, for<note n="n" place="margin">Iam. 2.16 Iob. 27.5.</note> 
                     <hi>the body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breath, is iudged dead.</hi> Breathing and mouing are ſignes of life.</p>
                  <p>The effects and motions of your life in Gods loue, will appeare, by the vſe and exerciſe of the graces of the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:18937:57"/> Spirit of God, which in his loue hee workes in you, to<note n="o" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.5, 6.</note> 
                     <hi>quicken and raiſe</hi> you from the death of ſin, to the life of righteouſneſſe. For this the Lord doth <hi>in his rich mercy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>and for his great loue wherewith he hath loued vs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe graces are of two ſorts. 1. Such as bring vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an actual communion of Gods loue and fauour, and ſets vs in the ſtate of grace. 2. Such as keepe &amp; preſerue in this ſtate vnto the end.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The firſt, Faith in Chriſt.</note>Of the graces of the firſt kind, namely, which bring vs into the ſtate of grace, there is but one onely, and it is a iuſtifying Faith, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, Faith in Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a ſinner, with <hi>a</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Matt. 11.28.</note> 
                     <hi>weary and heauy laden ſoule,</hi> that is,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:18937:57"/> a repenting and relenting heart goes and ſeekes to Chriſt for ſaluation, reſts and truſts in the merites of his death and righteouſnes for forgiueneſſe of ſinnes,<note place="margin">Ioa 3.16.</note> and eternall life.</p>
                  <p>This faith doth, not of it ſelfe: but by vertue of the obiect thereof, which is Chriſt, to whom, by Gods appointment it doth vnite and ingraft vs, in whom we are <hi>accepted</hi> and<note n="q" place="margin">Eph. 1.4.6.</note> 
                     <hi>beloued</hi> of God, and who <hi>dwells in your hearts by it.</hi> Now if<note n="r" place="margin">Eph. 3.17.</note> 
                     <hi>Chriſt dwell in your hearts by faith, you ſhall be able to comprehend with all Saints,</hi> what is <hi>the breadth and length,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>v.</hi> 18</note> 
                     <hi>and depth and height, and to know the loue of Chriſt which paſſeth knowledge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:18937:58"/>
                  <p>If you liue and die in this faith of Chriſt, then you may aſſure your ſelues you liue, and ſhall dy in the loue of God. For if yee beleeue in Chriſt, then this will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that, firſt, you <hi>are</hi>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">1. Ioh 5.1.</note> 
                     <hi>born of God:</hi> 2. yee <hi>are the</hi>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">Gal. 3.26.</note> 
                     <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God.</hi> 3. yee are<note n="x" place="margin">Act 13 39.</note> 
                     <hi>iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from all your ſinnes,</hi> and ſhall <hi>receiue remiſsion of them:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 10.43.</note> 4. Ye are <hi>paſſed</hi>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Iob. 3.36</note> 
                     <hi>from death to life:</hi> 5. Yee ſhall <hi>bee able to</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Eph. 6.16</note> 
                     <hi>quench all fiery darts of the deuil.</hi> And ſixtly, for the certainty of this, yee are<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 1.13</note> 
                     <hi>ſealed with the Spirit of promiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond ſort of graces that may aſſure vs wee ſhall dy in Gods fauour, are they which keepe and continue vs in the ſtate of grace whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:18937:58"/> we are ſet into it, and they are of foure kinds: The firſt, Sanctifying; The ſecond, Comforting; The third, Contenting; The fourth, Crowning graces: of which in order.</p>
                  <p>But firſt I would not bee miſtaken: for though, I ſay, faith in Chriſt doth ſet vs into the ſtate of grace, I would not bee vnderſtood to ſpeake excluſiuely, as if it had no worke in keeping vs alſo in that ſtate (for <hi>wee are kept by the power of God through faith vnto ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.5,</note>) But I haue therefore aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned vnto it, that worke of bringing vs into the ſtate of grace, and iuſtifying vs, becauſe the primary and chiefe act of it is this. <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:18937:59"/> To ingraft vs into Chriſt, and hereby to bring vs into vnion &amp; communion with the loue of God in him, and into the ſtate of grace, <hi>to liue by faith. Rom.</hi> 1.17.</p>
                  <p>The firſt kind of graces that keepe vs in the ſtate of grace, are ſanctifying gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo called, becauſe they keepe vs from ſinne, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite vs to holineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſanctifying graces are two: The firſt is the loue of God. The 2. is the feare of God: of each a litle. And firſt of loue vnto God.</p>
                  <p>What the nature of this grace of our loue to God is,<note place="margin">The ſecond, the Loue of God.</note> will appeare by the nature of our loue to any perſon like our ſelues, whom wee loue vnfainedly: our loue
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18937:59"/> appeare in two things. 1. In delighting in their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and communion. 2. In a deſire and indeuour to doe them good. For ſo are wee affected to God, if wee loue him, for we delight to be in his preſence and company in his Temple, and to haue communion with him in his Ordinances; the Word, Sacrament, Prayer, Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Thankſgiuing. 2. Wee deſire and will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to doe the beſt wee can, to honour and obey him; in refraining thoſe things that will diſpleaſe him, which is ſinne; and in practiſing all ſuch things as wee know will plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> him, which are comprehend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d vnder faith and obedience.</p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:18937:60"/>
                  <p>If wee haue this loue of God, and liue and dy ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, wee ſhall thereby be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured that we ſhal dy in the loue of God to vs. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will aſſure vs of the loue of God to vs.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.19</note> For <hi>we loue God becauſe hee loued vs firſt.</hi> 2. Becauſe it will aſſure vs, wee haue the Spirit of God, for loue is the<note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 5.22</note> 
                     <hi>fruite of the Spirit,</hi> and they who haue Gods<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 8.9</note> 
                     <hi>Spirit are Chriſts.</hi> 3. Becauſe it will aſſure vs our faith is ſound. For<note n="g" place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> 
                     <hi>faith is working</hi> and it <hi>works by loue.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.3</note> 4. Becauſe it, will aſſure vs that<note n="h" place="margin">Ro. 8.28.</note> 
                     <hi>all things ſhall worke together to good,</hi> namely, <hi>to the good of our ſaluation,</hi> for ſo doe <hi>they doe to them that loue God.</hi> 5. Becauſe it will aſſure vs we
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18937:60"/> 
                     <hi>are</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 8.3.</note> 
                     <hi>knowne of God,</hi> that is, acknowledged of him for his owne, for ſo are they that <hi>loue God.</hi> 6. Becauſe the Loue of God will aſſure vs of the <hi>crowne</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Iam. 1.12 &amp; 2, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>of life,</hi> and the kingdome of heauen; for it is promiſed, to <hi>them that loue God.</hi> 7. Becauſe it will aſſure vs, <hi>we</hi>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.7.</note> 
                     <hi>are borne of God,</hi> and are his children, yea that <hi>wee</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.19.</note> 
                     <hi>dwell in God, and that God dwels in vs.</hi> In which caſe whoſoeuer is, cannot but die in Gods loue and fauour, the rather, becauſe this loue of GOD produceth the loue of our neighbour alſo, yea of our enemyes; which whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doth for conſcience ſake, in action, as well as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, may knowe <hi>they are</hi>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:18937:61"/>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">1 Iohn 3.16. Matt. 5 44.</note> 
                     <hi>tranſlated from death to life,</hi> and that they are the child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren of their heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The third, is the Feare of God.</note>The ſecond ſanctifiyng grace, is the feare of God, (that is) feare to offend God, not onely becauſe he is iuſt: but alſo and cheifly becauſe <hi>he</hi>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Pſa. 130.2.</note> 
                     <hi>is mercifull.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this feare, Chriſtians learne <hi>to</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Pro. 3.7.</note> 
                     <hi>depart from euil,</hi> and alſo to<note n="n" place="margin">Deut. 6.2</note> 
                     <hi>keep Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements:</hi> which whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer doe,<note place="margin">2 Ti 2.19.</note> the <hi>Lord knowes that they are his,</hi> and they are the<note n="o" place="margin">Pſ. 112.1.</note> bleſſed of God.</p>
                  <p>If thus you feare God, you may bee ſure you ſhall dy in Gods loue and fauor, firſt, becauſe <hi>Gods mercy is on all them that feare him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 1.50.</note> 2. Becauſe it is a ſigne to all
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:18937:61"/> ſuch, that they are <hi>redeemed from their ſpirituall enemies,</hi> Sinne, Hell, Death, Satan. 3.<note place="margin">Luc. 7.14.</note> Becauſe ſuch <hi>walke in the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Act. 9.31.</note> Becauſe ſuch know <hi>they are redeemed by the precious blood of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.17 18, 19.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch <hi>worke out their ſaluation</hi> (that is) the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of it to themſelues.<note place="margin">Philip. 2.12</note> 6. Becauſe ſuch <hi>are bleſſed.</hi> And ſo much for the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying graces.<note place="margin">Pſ. 128.1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>I know faith in Chriſt is a ſanctifying grace, as well as the loue &amp; feare of God: for the Elect are <hi>ſanctified by faith in Chriſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 26.18.</note> But I haue named all theſe ſix graces, by the chiefe and moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per act of each, which of faith is to iuſtifie and not to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18937:62"/> ſanctifie. It is true, faith doth ſanctifie as well as iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie: but by a ſecondary act, not as it layes hold on Chriſt, for ſo it iuſtifies: but as it incites to obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and reſtrains from ſin: for which it produceth the loue and feare of God: for faith ſanctifies as it workes, and faith <hi>workes by loue:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> which alſo is true of the fear of God:<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> for by faith we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re Gods children, &amp; he is ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> adopted Father. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>call on the Father b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ith, then muſt wee paſſe the time of our ſoiourning heere in feare,</hi> namely, in feare to offend God by ſin.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.17</note> 
                     <hi>As obedient chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, not faſhioning our ſelues according to the former luſts in our ignorance.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">v. 14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:18937:62"/>
                  <p>Of the ſecond kinde of vertues &amp; holy gifts which keep vs in the ſtate of grace,<note place="margin">The third, is Hope.</note> when wee are ſet into it by faith there is but one, it is a comforting grace, and it is Hope,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4. <hi>vlt.</hi>
                     </note> and Hope is a grace of God, whereby we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelues againſt the immoderate feare of death in our ſelues, or greife for the death of our friendes; and by it the faithfull ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly looke, long, and will for the ſecond comming of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Act. 23.6. Rom. 5.2.</note> and a ioyfull reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from death, to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life thereby.</p>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer hath this Hope, may aſſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they ſhall dy in Gods favour. 1.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5.</note> Becauſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>will not make them aſhamed</hi> (that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:18937:63"/> is) they which by it looke for a ioyfull <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> it will not deceiue them of the thing hoped for; but will bring them to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeſſion of it. 2. Becauſe it is a ſure ſigne, that the loue of <hi>GOD is ſhed abroad in their hearts by the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 5.5.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.8</note> 3. Becauſe this hope is a <hi>helmet of ſaluation</hi> to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the heads of the Saints here one earth againſt Sin, Satan; and all ſpirituall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes. 4. Becauſe by this hope the faithfull aſſure themſelues their bodies <hi>are at reſt</hi> in the graue, till the ſecond comming of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Act. 2.26.</note> 5. Becauſe they <hi>are ſaued by hope.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.24.</note> 6. Becauſe he that hath this hope <hi>purgeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Iohn 33,</note> viz. from ſinne &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:18937:63"/> and he that thus purgeth himſelfe,<note place="margin">2 Ti. 2.21. Rom. 9.21</note> is a <hi>veſſel of honour,</hi> and hee that is a veſſell of honour,<note place="margin">Ibid. 23.</note> is a <hi>veſſell of mercy,</hi> and he that is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſell of mercy, is a veſſell <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore prepared vnto glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third kind of holy vertues that keepe vs in the ſtate of grace,<note place="margin">The fift, is Patience.</note> is the conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting grace, &amp; it is Patience. And by this patience, wee firſt quiet our ſelues in the will of God in all our afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and meekely ſubmit our ſelues to indure them. 2. By patience we ſtay our ſelues on Gods pleaſure, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently waiting his leaſure for the performance of his promiſe of helpe and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance.</p>
                  <p>If you haue and doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:18937:64"/> this patience, you may be ſure to die in Gods fauour.<note place="margin">Luk. 21.19</note> 1. Becauſe by it <hi>you poſſeſſe your ſoules.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2.7.</note> 2. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by it you ſhall <hi>gaine eternall life.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 6.12, 15.</note> 3. By <hi>patience you ſhall inherit the promiſes</hi> of grace and glory. 4. By patience we ſhall get <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 5.4.</note> namely, of the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue of God towards his children.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> 5. By patience we ſhall nouriſh and confirme <hi>our hope.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 1.4.</note> And 6th. Becauſe, <hi>if patience haue her perfect worke, wee ſhall be entire and lacke nothing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The ſixt, is Perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note>The fourth fort of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and holy gifts of the Spirit, that keepe vs in the ſtate of grace, when we are ſet into it by faith in Chriſt: It is a crowning
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18937:64"/> grace; and the grace that puts the crowne of glory on our heades, is perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the end of our liues, in the number &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all our Chriſtian gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, together with all the holy fruits and effects that proceed from them, in the vſe and exerciſe of them.</p>
                  <p>If you ſhall thus perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in grace, you may bee ſure to dy in Gods favour. 1.<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.24</note> Becauſe you <hi>ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the Sonne and in the Father.</hi> 2. Becauſe you <hi>ſhall bee ſaued</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.22</note> Becauſe you <hi>ſhall receiue the crowne of life.</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Reu. 2.10.</note> Becauſe the Lord Ieſus <hi>will preſent you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable and vnreproueable in Gods ſight.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">Col. 1.22.</note> Becauſe <hi>when Chriſt ſhall appeare,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.28</note> 
                     <hi>you
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:18937:65"/> may haue confidence, and not bee aſhamed before him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> his comming.</hi> 6. If yee <hi>fight a good fight, finiſh your courſe, and keepe the faith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.</note> then you may aſſure your ſelues that <hi>henceforth is laid vp for you a crowne of righteouſnes, which the Lord the righteous Iudge will giue you at that day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There be other graces of God that are neceſſary to ſaluation, viz. a beleife of the Goſpell, &amp; repentance for paſt ſinnes, (I doe not meane amendment of life or new obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture follow Faith in Chriſt) but theſe doe not ſet men into the ſtate of grace: but onely diſpoſe them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and vnto faith which doth ſet men therein, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18937:65"/> therfore haue I not menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned them here, becauſe it is poſſible for a man to haue theſe, and yet not dye in the ſtate of grace, if hee dy before he haue faith in Chriſt, and the other bee wrought in him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can you not aſſure your ſelues, that you dy in Gods fauour if you ſtay here, and haue not the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſixe.</p>
                  <p>There be alſo beſides, a beleife of the goſpell, and repentance for paſt ſinnes, ſome other graces that doe follow it as effects &amp; fruits thereof, namely, peace of conſcience, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt; and theſe alſo are helpes to preſerue vs in the ſtate of grace. For <hi>that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18937:66"/> peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding</hi> (and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the ioy of GOD,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.7.</note> which is,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.8.</note> 
                     <hi>vnſpeakable &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> (doth <hi>keepe our hearts and minds in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But theſe graces imply comfort more then duty, &amp; I had rather that Chriſtians ſhould endeauour to aſſure themſelues they ſhall die in Gods fauour, by graces that import duty; then by them which import co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort: leaſt ſome Chriſtians tender in conſcience, not finding the graces of comfort, may therfore think they haue no grace, nor are in the ſtate of grace, which is vſua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l with ſuch to thinke of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, ſpecially in affliction, &amp; vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of temptation: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18937:66"/> indeed as long as the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull graces exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in them, they may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure themſelues they ſhall die in Gods fauour, though they want the feeling of their ioyfull and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble graces for the time, ſo they hunger for them, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after them, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in the vſe of the means to get them.</p>
                  <p>In like manner, beſides all the forenamed graces and holy gifts of the Spirit, there be ſome vertuous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Chriſtian duties,<note place="margin">Vertuous actions, that will aſſure vs to dy in Gods fauor.</note> to which the godly are ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp continually by the Spirit, and by the means of the ſix forenamed graces; and by the conſtant &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable practiſe whereof,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18937:67"/> they may rather aſſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they liue in Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uour, &amp; conſequently ſhall dye therein. I will but only touch them.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 10.9. Heb 10.23</note>1. A zealous profeſſion of the Goſpel, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſlaunder and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger accompanying it.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 6.6. Ier. 50.4.5 6. 2 Reg. 23.3</note>2. Often renewing our <hi>couenant</hi> with God of new obedience, by ſearching our hearts and liues for our ſins, and lamenting our back-ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Deuout intention of mind,<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.6.7.8.84.</note> and inſtant affection of heart in Gods ſeruice and worſhip,<note place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> in all the points and kinds of it, publike, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate, or ſecret, ordinary or extraordinary.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <note place="margin">Matt. 5.24.50.</note>4. Mortifying our ſinful
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18937:67"/> nature, and leſſoning our will and power to ſinne, by croſſing our owne wills, to the end we may doe Gods, and denying to our ſelues the occaſions and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of our beloued ſins.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Growing in grace,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.18 &amp; 5.10, 12</note> and increaſing in the number and meaſure of our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an vertues and holy graces.</p>
                  <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">1 Pet 5.7.8</note> A ſober moderating of our affections about worldly profits, pleaſures, and honors, that our hearts be not ſet too much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
                  <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">1 Cor 7.31 30.39.</note> Diligent faithfulneſſe and conſcionableneſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Iuſtice, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie in doing our duty in our ordinary callings: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Common-wealth,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.24</note>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:18937:68"/> Church,<note place="margin">Col. 3.18, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 22.</note> or Family.</p>
                  <p>But all theſe are the fruits and effects of the ſixe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named graces, &amp; they ſhew the ſoundneſſe and ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of them, and therefore are neceſſarily implied in them: and for as much as they are not habits or ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues themſelues, but actions of thoſe vertues and graces; and alſo, for becauſe the forenamed ſixe (with their vſe and exerciſe) are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to aſſure vs that we ſhall die in Gods fauour; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue I forborne to ſpeake of them at large, as I haue done of the other ſix. The rather becauſe theſe ſixe are ſufficient to free vs from all euils, ſin, affliction, death, hell, and the deuill:
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:18937:68"/> and to make vs partakers of all good things; as grace, peace, glory, and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>But to draw towards an end: We doe all owe God a death; this debt is to be paid when God will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it. The Lord reſpects not (&amp; therefore what need we ſtand on it) in what coyn we pay our debt, gold or ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſo it be his own ſtampe, and bee weight with the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance (that is) what need we be troubled what death we die,<note place="margin">Num. 23.1</note> ſo it bee the <hi>death of the rigtheous:</hi> which God himſelfe ſends, and not we our ſelues pull vpon our ſelues, through our owne ſins, and ſo it be <hi>in the faith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11.13</note> with truſt and confidence
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:18937:69"/> for the allowance and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, of the death and obedience of Ieſus Chriſt to our iuſtification; for what euer our death be, wee ſhall be happy in it. Be it ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or extraordinary; of an Ague, or the Plague, in the bed, or in the field, in the Citie or in the Countrey, a naturall or a violent death.</p>
                  <p>And thus much by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your preſent Griefe &amp; Feare, to pacifie the one, and to ſatisfie the other; and further to ſanctifie &amp; ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both to your future edification, by humiliation or conſolation in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Of theſe Meditations, which God by his Spirit hath miniſtred vnto mee, I
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18937:69"/> may ſay as Phyſicians do of their medicines, <hi>Probatum eſt</hi> (that is) They haue been proued, and approued by the ſeruants of GOD, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we read in the Word, out of which they are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by, and my Selfe in this preſent Viſitation of my ſeruants, children, &amp; louing Aſſiſtant, whom the Lord hath taken to <hi>reſt from his labours in his Vineyard</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,<note place="margin">Math. 20.12.</note> and hath giuen him his wages for his worke (as it were) but one houre therein, <hi>Matt.</hi> 20.12.</p>
                  <p>What remaines, but that as I haue made the potion, and ſent it, ſo you take and apply it. And becauſe I haue taken paines to write theſe Meditation for you,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:18937:70"/> that therefore you will take care to read &amp; peruſe them, to ponder and conſider of them ſeriouſly for your ſelues and your own good, to confer the points with the proofs, and to compare your ſelues with the points, that you may receiue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther direction and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according as the nature of the ſeuerall points ſhall lead you, and your particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar need require. To the end you may (by laying your ſelues to the Rule) find iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter cauſe of humiliation in your ſelues, or of conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>If you ſhall lay them cloſe to your hearts, I doubt not, but as they haue miniſtred comfort and content to vs,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:18937:70"/> (for which wee praiſe our good God) ſo will they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, by his bleſſing. (For which I will not ceaſe to pray.)</p>
                  <p>But (before I end,) I would take my leaue of you by ſaying one thing more vnto you, according as your houſes haue beene cleare (all this while) or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited, and your ſelues ſound or infected, and that which I will ſay, ſhall be firſt vnto you all, of both ſorts ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and then vnto each ſort of you in ſeverall.</p>
                  <p>That which concernes you altogether, is a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word and a Requeſt.</p>
                  <p>My watch-word is to warne you, not to cenſure your brethren that haue
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:18937:71"/> been either infected when you were cleere, or viſited more heauily then your ſelues, or taken away by the viſitation when you ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viue, as if they <hi>were greater ſinners,</hi> then you for this were to bee <hi>miſerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forters,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luc. 13.2, 4 Iob. 16.2.</note> when you ſhould be comforters of them in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. Yea, it is to trample on them, whom God hath caſt downe.</p>
                  <p>My requeſt is, that you would (according to your abillitie) with your handes releiue their povertie, as well as in heart pitty them. for that is charitie. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you are called, not onely by the word, which bids you Loue <hi>indeed,</hi> as well <hi>as in word,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ioa. 3.18</note> &amp; affection
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18937:71"/> only, but alſo by the extreme penurie wherein too many haue bin, are, &amp; will be caſt;<note place="margin">Luc. 2.16.</note> partly by ſickneſſe, partly by decay of trade, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by approching winter.</p>
                  <p>That which ſhall be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of each ſort o you in ſeuerall, ſhall be firſt to them that haue not ben vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited all this while, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them that are recouered and eſcaped from death, though you were viſited.</p>
                  <p>To you whoſe houſes haue yet been free, I would giue an admonition, and an exhortation.</p>
                  <p>My admonition is, That you would not be ſecure, as if God now could not ſmite you: For there were firſt in this Viſitation, that ſhall
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:18937:72"/> not be laſt, and there ſhall be laſt that were not firſt.</p>
                  <p>And my exhortation is, That you neuer forget the free fauour of God in your protection &amp; preſeruation: (leaſt he repent him of the good hee hath done vnto you:) But that you ſtudie <hi>what you ſhall render to the Lord for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> his benefits,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 116.12</note> and endeuour to expreſſe your thankfulneſſe for ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance by ſeruing him, <hi>you and your houſhold</hi> more conſtantly &amp; conſcionably.<note place="margin">Ioſh. 24.15</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>To you whoſe houſes haue been viſited, and yet your ſelues are eſcaped and enioy your liues ſo a pray, I would likewiſe giue you a caution and a counſell.</p>
                  <p>My caution is, that you
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:18937:72"/> thinke not that any thing in your ſelues, or in your meanes, hath made the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt you that are aliue, and other that are dead; for this were <hi>to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to your ſelues,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Abac. 1.16</note> and <hi>to your net and yarne.</hi> But that God his free favour, his power and goodneſſe: hath made the difference; who will haue mery on whom hee will, and who can preſerue whom he pleaſeth.</p>
                  <p>And my counſell is, That during the time of your liues hereafter,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 30.17.</note> you <hi>ſet your hearts to ſeeke God,</hi> and make him your <hi>portion and inheritance,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 116.5.</note> 
                     <hi>walke within your houſes with a perfect heart;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 101.2.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.14.</note> and <hi>ſin no more leaſt a worſe thing come vnto you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:18937:73"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2 The. 2.16</note>Now <hi>our Lord Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, and God euen our Father, which hath ſaued vs, and giuen vs euerlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; comfort your hearts, and ſtabliſh you in euery good word and worke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Bleſſed bee God, euen the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.3, 4.</note> 
                     <hi>the Father of mercies, and the GOD of all comf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rt, who comforteth vs in all our tribulation, that wee may bee able to comfort them which are in trouble, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vvherewith wee our ſelues are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted of God;</hi> Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:73"/>
                  <p>AN HVMBLE THANKS-GIVING TO ALMIGHTIE GOD:</p>
                  <p>For his ſo ſoone, ſo great, and ſo gracious ſtaying of the Plague, in the Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and Subvibs thereof.</p>
                  <p>BY WILLIAM CHIBALD.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 36.1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>O giue thankes vnto the Lord, for he is good: for his mercy endureth for euer.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Printed at London by <hi>W. I.</hi> for <hi>Nic. Bourne,</hi> and <hi>Edw. Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>wſter,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Royall Exchange, and at the Bible in Pauls-Church-yard. 1625.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:74"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:74"/>
                  <head>The Preface.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE more deadly a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is, the greater is the Cure; and the greater the Cure is, the greater is the commendation of the Phyſician. Euen ſo the greater any danger is, the greater is GODs deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb facs="tcp:18937:75"/> from it, the greater ought to bee our Thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing vnto his bleſſed Maieſty for it.</p>
                  <p>On theſe, and the like grounds, J haue formerly ſtirred vp my ſelfe vnto ſecret, priuate, and publike giuing of thankes to our good God, for abating the heat of the ſicknes, &amp; the number of them that dye thereof. And ſynce, J haue endeauoured to forward others alſo to glorifie God in this behalfe, by penning a forme thereof, and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing
<pb facs="tcp:18937:75"/> it, with this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. The rather becauſe J haue not ſeen nor heard of any thing in this kind ſet forth for publike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefyt.</p>
                  <p>The time and meanes of grace conſidered, J thinke J may truely ſay (for the generalitie) that ſynne did neuer ſo abound in quantitie, qualitie, and variety, as of late it hath done in our Citie of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and the Suburbs thereof. And now (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold) anſwerable to the
<pb facs="tcp:18937:76"/> meaſure of our ſynnes, is the meaſure of Gods Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſytation, for there was neuer ſuch a plague ſent among vs.</p>
                  <p>Jn like manner the contagion and maligni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this Plague con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydered, which in ſo ſhort a time, when ſo many vvere abſent, killed ſo many thouſands: J may ſafely ſay there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuch a Deliuerance in this kinde vvrought by Almightie GOD for vs: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d therefore anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:18937:76"/> to Gods great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ought to be our great gratefulnes.</p>
                  <p>Now, conſydering (Chriſtian Reader) that the meaſure of our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to GOD, ought to be ſo great, and that our power (as of our ſelues) to performe it, is ſo ſmall Let vs all that <hi>want ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 1.</note> for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,<note place="margin">1 Ti. 1.17</note> 
                     <hi>aske of God onely wiſe,</hi> that hee would bee pleaſed to giue vs in abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, what he requires of vs in dutie, and that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations
<pb facs="tcp:18937:77"/> of my heart in conceiuing of this forme, and the vvordes of our mouthes in vttering it, may bee directed by his bleſſed Spirit, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his beloued Sonne, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Reg. 1.36</note> And <hi>let the Lord God</hi> of our Citie, and our deliuerance <hi>ſay ſo too.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:77"/>
                  <head>The parts of the Thankſgiuing for this Deliuerance, are SIXE.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>I. BEmoning our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, cauſed by the Plague.</item>
                     <item>II. Confeſſing our ſinnes that brought it.</item>
                     <item>III. Acknowledging Gods Iuſtice in ſending the Plague.</item>
                     <item>IV. Thanking GODs goodneſſe for ſtaying it.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18937:78"/>
                     <item>V. Praying to GOD, wholly to remooue the Plague.</item>
                     <item>VI. Profeſſing our amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the remoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thereof.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18937:78"/>
                  <head>A THANKES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIVING TO GOD, FOR STAYING the Plague.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD GOD of Heauen and earth, by whoſe patience &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence it is, that yet <hi>vvee liue, and moue,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 17.28</note> 
                     <hi>and haue our being</hi> in this world: for <hi>our life drew nigh vnto the graue,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 88.3, 4</note> 
                     <hi>and wee were counted with them that goe downe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pit.</hi> Through thy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18937:79"/> goodneſſe (O Lord) <hi>wee are a remnant eſcaped,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezra 9.15.</note> 
                     <hi>as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth this day,</hi> reſerued (as wee truſt) to glorifie thy Name. But who are wee, <hi>daſt and aſhes,</hi> miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that ſhould be bold to glorifie thy goodneſſe, that deſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e not to confeſſe our owne vildeneſſe: being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, as of the Deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ance it ſelfe, ſo to giue thee thankes for it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>I.</hi> Bemoning our miſery, cauſed by the Plague.</note>Our vildeneſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe appears by our great and many ſinnes, and the haynouſnes of our ſins, by thy late dealing with vs in heauy diſpleaſure. <hi>Our ſoule hauing in remembrance our affliction and miſery,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lam. 3.19, 20.</note> 
                     <hi>the wormewood and the gaull is humbled in vs:</hi> For thou
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18937:79"/> haſt ſent <hi>the plague among vs after the manner of Egypt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos 4.10</note> in moſt grieuous manner, the like was neuer before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs. Thou haſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viſited vs with Agues and Feuers,<note place="margin">Eze. 14.21</note> 
                     <hi>but with one of thy foure ſore iudgements;</hi> The Plague or Peſtilence, <hi>a conſuming ſickneſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deu. 23.21</note> by which thou haſt <hi>powred out thy fury in blood vpon vs.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eze. 14.19.</note> With it bane been infected all the Pariſhes of our Citie and Suburbs ſaue one) and of it haue dyed <hi>and fallen thouſands at our ſides,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.7.</note> 
                     <hi>and ten thouſands at our right hand:</hi> rich and poore, young and old, profane and ſincere, profeſſours and preachers. The chiefe and Princes of the Cities of our Nation, is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18937:80"/> ſolitary &amp; ſits as a widdow: She that was full of People, is emptie of Inhabitants; the ſtreets thereof mourne, and the high wayes to it la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the publike markets are not frequented, and the ſolemne Aſſemblies of thy worſhip are much deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; darkned, by the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of many worthy Lights, his faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. At home, ô Lord, ſom haue periſhed for want of keeping, and abroad ſome haue fallen downe dead in the feilds and ſtreets. One of ſome houſes (O Lord God) haue dyed all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, Parents and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Maſters and ſeruants, and in other, all haue bin ſicke at once, not one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18937:80"/> to help another. In ſom familyes might bee heard, the out-cry of the tender mother, for her onely child and in other, the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the carefull father, for the death of his ſonne and heire, or the child, that was the picture of his like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Yea, ſuch and ſo great was our greife and feare (O Lord) that when wee went to bed well, wee looked to bee ſmitten ere morning, and could take little reſt for the noiſe of bells, towling &amp; ringing out in our eares. And when wee aroſe in health in the morning, we expected to be caſt downe ere night, and could not follow our callings chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for the ſight of our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18937:81"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18937:81"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18937:82"/> eyes, multituds of our dead brethren and ſiſters, caried vp and downe the ſtreets to buriall. Wee doe not (O Lord God) repeate theſe our calamityes to informe thee, as if thou, who didſt bring them vpon vs, didſt not know of them, or hadſt forgotten them: but that we might not forget them, nor thy heauy diſpleaſure againſt our ſinnes in them, that wee might bee made more ſenſible of our great deliuerance, by calling to minde our former danger and diſtreſſe, and thereby alſo the better prepared to a more free, and humble confeſſion of our ſins,<note place="margin">Eze. 12.16</note> that haue brought theſe cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities vpon vs.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:18937:82"/>
                  <p>For wee muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe (O Lord our God) to thy glory and our owne ſhame,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>II.</hi> Confeſsing our ſins, that brought the Plague.</note> that we haue practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thoſe ſinnes, againſt which, in thy Word, this plague is threatned, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the committers where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it hath beene executed, in former Ages of the Church. For in all duties, concerning thy ſacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, our brethren, and our owne ſelues,<note place="margin">Ezek 14.13.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Wee haue ſinned by treſpaſsing grieuouſly,</hi> and therefore haſt thou ſent the plague,<note place="margin">Eze. 38.22</note> &amp; <hi>with the peſtilence pleaded againſt vs, in blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee haue not (O Lord our GOD) <hi>ſacrificed vnto thee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 5.3.</note> nor worſhipped thee ſo frequently, nor ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly as wee ſhould, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18937:83"/> haſt thou <hi>fallen vpon vs by the peſtilence,</hi> and many of vs <hi>haue defiled thy ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 5.11</note> the place of thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, when wee haue reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereunto with <hi>our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable things,</hi> our abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſinnes, impenitencie, and hypocriſie, and therfore <hi>a great part of vs haue dyed by the peſtilence</hi> in this viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Vnto our brethren we haue beene cruell, and haue <hi>not proclaimed libertie to them that were</hi> in our dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger;<note place="margin">Ier. 34.5.17.</note> therefore the Lord hath <hi>proclaimed libertie to the peſtilence for many of vs.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 14.10.12.</note> And we our ſelues haue <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted to wander in our own wayes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 14.10.12.</note> and to take pleaſure in ſin for a ſeaſon, and <hi>haue not refrained our feet from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18937:83"/> paths:</hi> Therfore <hi>the Lord hath not accepted vs, hee hath remembred our iniquity, hath viſited our ſinnes, and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs by the peſtilence.</hi> With <hi>Pharaoh</hi> wee haue <hi>hardned</hi> our hearts againſt thy mercies &amp; iudgements,<note place="margin">Exod. 9.</note> and haue not beene reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from our ſinnes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, we haue not let <hi>our luſts goe that we might ſerue thee;</hi> nor <hi>let our brethren goe, that they might ſerue thee.</hi> But haue diſcouraged &amp; cooled their Zeale in thy ſeruice, therefore haſt thou <hi>ſmitten vs by the peſtilence,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>and cut off many from off the earth.</hi> Wee haue <hi>with Iſrael murmured againſt Moſes &amp; Aaron,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nu 16.21.</note> our Magiſtrates and Miniſters, for their zeale in correcting
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18937:84"/> and reprouing our vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous dealing, &amp; inordinate walking, and there haue <hi>dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many thouſands</hi> of the plague,<note place="margin">Nu 16.42</note> 
                     <hi>beſides thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y</hi> of other diſeaſes. With the Spies of the Land of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Num. 14.37.36.</note> wee haue <hi>brought vp an euill report</hi> vpon thy holy Maieſty, thy Church, and holy Ordinances,<note place="margin">Pſ. 50.31.</note> as if <hi>thou wert like the wicked,</hi> as if thy Church were a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of none but Hypocrites and Rebels, and as if thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ordinances were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy things, &amp; taught pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſſe, and therefore <hi>by bringing vp this ſlander vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy Name,</hi> through our looſeneſſe and vnconſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable life <hi>many are dead of the plague before the Lord.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nu. 14 37.</note>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:18937:84"/> As Magiſtrates, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Husbands and Wiues, Parents and Children, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Seruants, rich and poore, high and low, young and old, one with another. <hi>We haue not obeyed thy voyce,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 32.23 24.</note> 
                     <hi>nor walked in thy Law. Wee haue done nothing at all, that thou haſt commaunded vs to doe:</hi> and therfore <hi>what thou haſt ſpoken in thy Word of the peſtilence, it is come to paſſe, and thou ſeeſt it,</hi> and wee haue felt it.<note place="margin">Deu. 25.21</note> Yea wee <hi>would not obſerue to doe all thy commandements and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, which thou comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest vs to do,</hi> but haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them all in one kinde and meaſure or other. And therefore <hi>haſt thou made the peſtilence cleaue vnto vs till</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid.</note>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:18937:85"/> 
                     <hi>it hath conſumed vs. We haue not harkened vnto thy words,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 29.19.17.</note> 
                     <hi>which thou haſt ſent unto vs, by thy ſeruants the Prophets</hi> or Paſtors &amp; teachers,<note place="margin">Leu. 26.23.</note> when they haue called vs vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, nor haue we <hi>been reformed</hi> by leſſer correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>but walked contrary unto thee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iere. 29.18</note> therefore haſt thou <hi>perſecuted us with the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Leu. 26.25</note> and <hi>ſent it vnto our Cities, where we haue ben ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together.</hi> We doe not (O Lord our God) thus confeſſe our ſins vnto thee, as if thou kneweſt them not <hi>who art greater then our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences &amp; knoweſt althings.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.20</note> but that by the repetition and remembrance of them, we might be drawne, more ſoundly to repent of them,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18937:85"/> and to haue our eyes open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, more cleerely to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne thy iuſtice, in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of vs with this thy viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in afflicting vs with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſeries thereby,<note place="margin">Pſ. 52.4.</note> that <hi>thou mayeſt bee cleare when thou art iudged.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 9.7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>For <hi>Righteouſnes belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto thee</hi> (O Lord) <hi>but vnto us open ſhame as at this day.</hi> All this is <hi>come vpon us,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>III.</hi> Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging Gods Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Plague.</note> 
                     <hi>for our euill deedes,</hi> and for our <hi>great treſpaſſes, and thou haſt puniſhed vs leſſe then our iniquities deſerue,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier 9.13.</note> therefore <hi>will wee be dumbe and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our mouthes.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 39.9.</note> Thou <hi>haſt not done without cauſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 14.28.</note> 
                     <hi>all that thou haſt done</hi> vnto vs,<note place="margin">Lev. 26.43</note> and <hi>therefore will wee accept the puniſhment of our iniquitie.</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18937:86"/> Though thou haſt not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed vs according to the greatneſſe of our ſinnes as they deſerue in meaſure, (which is thy mercy,) yet haſt thou puniſhed vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the kind &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our ſinnes (which is thy iuſtice) for we haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned thy houſe and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie, with our formall and hypocriticall ſeruing of thee, without the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward partes both of our ſelues, and of thy worſhip, and therefore haſt thou ſhut the dores of thy houſe vpon vs, when we were vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited, and haſt (by lawfull authoritie and good order) ſhut vs vp in our owne hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.<note place="margin">Pſa. 101.2</note> In our <hi>owne houſes wee haue not walked before thee,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18937:86"/> with a perfect heart,</hi> for falſe weights and meaſures, falſe lights and bad wares, haue been in many of our ſhops and ware-houſes, and therefore it is iuſt with thee to ſhutt vp our ſhopps for want of trading, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect other of our roomes, and chambers, with a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full contagion. Many of vs that were wont, proudly to let and ſtrutt it out in the ſtreetes, in the vanitie and varietie of ſtrange apparell, and new fangled habits and attyres, haſt thou now clad with mourning weeds and giuen vs cauſe to put ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth on our backs, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes on our heads, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> we are baaſed even to the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill. The members of our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18937:87"/> bodyes, we haue abuſed as weapons of vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto ſinne, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haſt thou (O Lord) weakened and deformed the bodies of ſome with blanes and ſores, boyles and carbuncles, and filled the bodies of others with the <hi>Tokens</hi> of thy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. We haue corrupted one another wirh the euill example of our workes, and <hi>made them ſinne;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is iuſt (with thee) that we ſhould be a meanes to infect one another to ſickneſſe and death. Many of our Miniſters, thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſeruants, wee regarded not while they liued, and therefore haſt thou depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs of them: yea, many
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18937:87"/> of vs haue defrauded them of their <hi>double honour,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Ti. 5.17.</note> reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend reſpect, and plentifull maintenance; and therfore haſt thou taken from vs the means of our maintenance, by commerce and traffique. Wee haue been hard-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and cloſe-fiſted to the neceſſities of our poore neighbours liuing amongſt vs; and therefore it is iuſt, (in reſpect of thee) that our neighbour countries round about vs, did deny to bring vs (that abode in the Citie) food and victualls, and to bury thoſe of vs that did go out of it, with comely buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Wee haue by our bad liuing and vniuſt dealing, cauſed thy Goſpel, thy <hi>truth</hi> (ſo plentifully prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.2.</note>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:18937:88"/> in this Citie) <hi>to bee euill ſpoken of</hi> abroad, and therfore it is iuſt with thee, that wee ſhould bee a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and hiſſing, a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word and a reproach vnto our neighbour countries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs. Wee doe not (O Lord God) thus iuſtifie thy proceeding againſt vs, as if it needed our cleering: but to teſtifie our deſire (as much as poſſible wee can) to glorifie thy iuſtice by ſhaming our ſelues, to the end wee may bee the better prepared to glorifie thy mercy alſo (which <hi>is aboue all thy workes</hi>) in our won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull deliuerance.<note place="margin">Pſa. 145.9</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>IV.</hi> Thanking Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Plague.</note>For (O Lord our God) In that when the ſickneſſe was ſo hot, and ſo many
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18937:88"/> had dyed thereof, thou ſhouldeſt then ſtay it: It was not becauſe the ſword of thine Angel was blunted with ſo many ſtrokes; or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there were no more people to dye, or <hi>no more graues in London:</hi> or becauſe there was in vs no more deſert of puniſhment,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.11.</note> or in thee no more power to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh: But becauſe thou wert pleaſed <hi>in iudgement to remember mercy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Abac. 3.2.</note> and that thou <hi>delighteſt in mercy</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then iudgement.<note place="margin">Mica. 7.18.</note> That wee are aliue when others are dead, that wee were in health when others were ſicke. It was not becauſe wee were not within the compaſſe of thy ſtroke, or could defend our ſelues, or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18937:89"/> were able to heale the wound: But <hi>becauſe thou wouldſt haue mercy on whom thou wouldſt:</hi> no goodneſſe or power in vs, but meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly greatneſſe and goodneſſe in thee, hath made the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. And therefore, as thou <hi>art worthy to receiue glory,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 4.11.</note> 
                     <hi>honour, and power:</hi> ſo <hi>ſaluation, and glory, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and power,</hi> (euen glory and honour for manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy power in our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and preſeruation,<note place="margin">2. Chr. 7.14</note>) <hi>bee vnto thee,</hi> for euer. For in this our deliuerance (O Lord our God) we ſee, and therefore deſire to glorifie thy wiſedome, in putting it into the minde of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours to appoint thine owne means of healing our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18937:89"/> Citie by humiliation with Faſting and Prayer, and enabling thy Miniſters and people vnderſtandingly &amp; feelingly, faithfully and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently to vſe thoſe meanes, and alſo in taking oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie in our greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie to worke this our deliuerance, to the end the worke might the more cleerely appeare to be thine owne. In this thy deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance we diſcerne thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and therfore according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wee deſire to praiſe thee, in that thou art able to countermand all thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, euen the very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, <hi>thoſe principalities and powers:</hi> for thou didſt on a ſodaine, and in a ſhort time worke a great deliuerance,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18937:90"/> notwithſtanding the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull increaſe of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion in ſo many places, the heate of the weather, the multitude of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and heynouſneſſe of our ſins, all which wrought toward a contrary end. In this thy deliuerance, wee behold thy truth and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe (O Lord our God) in making good thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of <hi>healing thy people,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Chr. 7.15.</note> when they ſhall <hi>ſeeke thy face with prayers, teares, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation,</hi> and <hi>turning vnto thee,</hi> in not <hi>keeping thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for euer,</hi> in not letting the <hi>rod of the wicked reſt for euer vpon vs all,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 103.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 105.</note> nor <hi>ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy people to bee tempted aboue their ſtrength, but gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a good iſſue of their try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18937:90"/> In this our deliuerance we glorifie thy patience, in that thou haſt not dealt <hi>with vs according to our ſins,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 103.11.</note> 
                     <hi>nor rewarded vs after our iniquities;</hi> but haſt borne with vs all this while, and giuen vs yet a longer time to repent, <hi>ſparing vs, as a father ſpareth his owne ſonne that ſerueth him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 3.17.</note> In this thy deliuerance (O heauenly Father) wee ſee alſo thy pittie, in that, when our great ſinnes had deſerued the greateſt and foreſt of thy foure plagues, euen the ſword; that yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thou didſt ſend but the ſmalleſt of them: for hereby wee are <hi>not fallen into the hands of</hi> men,<note place="margin">Prou.</note> 
                     <hi>whoſe mercies are Cruelties;</hi> but,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18937:91"/> 
                     <hi>into thy hands, whoſe mercies are great:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.</note> haſt already wonderfully leſſened this thy hand, and haſt alſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs good hope (through grace) of quite remouing the ſame. But aboue all, (O Lord our God) In this our deliuerance felt and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, we cleerely behold thy free grace, and rich fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, with thy infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and vnſpeakable loue, (and accordingly we deſire to bee plentious in thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving) for when there was no goodnes in vs to moue thee to it, nor power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it to our ſelues; Yea when iuſtice on thy part, and wickedneſſe on ours, did withſtand it, then thou waſt pleaſed <hi>to thinke
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18937:91"/> thoughts of</hi> peace towards vs, and to <hi>ſtay thy hand,</hi> to ſay to vs,<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.6</note> 
                     <hi>when we were pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted in our</hi> bloud, <hi>Liue.</hi> When the <hi>fornace</hi> of thy diſpleaſure was heated,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> much hotter, then euer it was before, and the <hi>flame thereof,</hi> had conſumed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our neighbours hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet on ſome of our houſes <hi>the fire had no power</hi> at all, nor was a hayre of <hi>the heads of many of vs ſynged;</hi> wee ayled nothing all the while,<note place="margin">Pſa. 115.1.</note> and therfore <hi>not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs</hi> (O Lord) <hi>not vnto vs, but vnto thy Name bee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen all the praiſe.</hi> Not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Phyſicians or Surgeons: Not vnto Magiſtrates or Miniſters; Not to Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or Keepers, not to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidotes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18937:92"/> or preſeruatiues, not to houſe or ayre, not to Signes or Planets, not to Saints or Angels, not to our ſelues or others. Not thy workes in vs of nature or grace; no, not to our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and prayers, to our humiliation &amp; teares: But to thy wiſedome and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to thy faithfulneſſe and truth, to thy patience and pittie, to thy free grace and rich mercy, be giuen by vs all, and by all meanes in all times, and in all places, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and glory, with thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing and obedience, in Ieſus Chriſt, from this time forth and for euer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>V.</hi> Praying to God w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>remone the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>And now (heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) ſeeing wee <hi>that are but duſt and Aſhes, haue taken
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18937:92"/> vpon us to ſpeake</hi> vnto thee in thankſgiuing,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.18.</note> 
                     <hi>bee not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with vs,</hi> if we <hi>ſpeake once more</hi> in prayer and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation alſo, we rather hope thou wilt bee pleaſed with vs,<note place="margin">Pſa. 116.13.</note> if hauing <hi>taken the cup of ſaluation</hi> in thankefulneſſe for ſtaying the plague ſo ſoone, and ſo much already wee alſo call <hi>vpon the Name of the Lord</hi> for the quite re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueall thereof.<note place="margin">P. 2.125.4</note> The <hi>rod of the wicked</hi> hath long lyen vpon vs; Oh let <hi>it not reſt</hi> vpon vs that are the <hi>lot</hi> of thine inheritance: for thou haſt ſaid,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7. Esay. 29.5.25.</note> Thou <hi>wilt not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the ſeed of Dauid for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</hi> Thy <hi>hand is ſtretched out ſtill,</hi> Oh wee pray thee pull it in, and put it into thy boſome, for we haue beene
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18937:93"/> 
                     <hi>conſumed by the heauineſſe of it.</hi> Thou haſt formerly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs many great deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, to this Citie in this kind, &amp; to the whole Land in other kindes, namely, from forraine inuaſion and priuy conſpiracie;<note place="margin">The Spaniſh Armado. <hi>1588.</hi> The Gun-powder-Treaſon. <hi>1605.</hi>
                     </note> and wee confeſſe to thy glory, and and our owne ſhame, that moſt of vs haue almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten to celebrate the memoriall of them; &amp; none of vs haue euer ſince led our liues (which thou didſt preſerue from the crueltie of thoſe intendments and attempts) in righteouſneſſe and holineſſe before thee. And in this reſpect wee are vnworthy thou ſhouldſt proceed in mercy, as thou haſt begun; &amp; end in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18937:93"/> as thou haſt proceeded: But though wee be vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of more deliuerance, yet art thou worthy of more honor, which accordingly thou ſhalt receiue. For by how much the more we are vnworthy, by ſo much the more doth the freeneſſe &amp; greatneſſe of thy grace and mercy appeare; and by how much the more thy grace &amp; mercy appeares free and great, by ſo much the more doth the glory thereof ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare for thine honor. And therfore (O Lord our God) <hi>though our iniquities teſtifie againſt vs:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 14.7. 1 Sa. 12.21</note> 
                     <hi>yet do it for thine owne Names ſake, forſake not thy people for thy great names ſake,</hi> becauſe <hi>it hath pleaſed thee to make vs thy people.</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18937:94"/> Thou art an exquiſite worke-man, leaue not thy worke halfe done as if thou couldſt not finiſh it, but end it in perfection. Thou art an abſolute Phyſician, leaue not thy Patients crazy &amp; ſickly, till thou haſt made a perfect Cure. And that thou maiſt perfect the work of deliuerance, which thou haſt begun amongſt vs, wee beſeech thee perfect the works of grace and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which thou haſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun within vs. Thou haſt already ſaid to thine Angel, <hi>Stay thy hand:</hi> for this wee praiſe thee, bee pleaſed alſo to goe on and to ſay, <hi>It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,</hi> for this we pray thee command thine Angel alſo <hi>to put vp his ſword into the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.16.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">1. Chron. 21.7</note>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18937:94"/> 
                     <hi>ſheath thereof</hi> and to draw it out no more. <hi>Returne, O Lord, how long? let it repent thee concerning thy ſeruants,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa 90.13.15.</note> make vs <hi>glad according to the dayes wherein thou haſt afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs,</hi> and the months and weekes wherin <hi>we haue ſeen euill.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lam. 5.21.</note> 
                     <hi>Renew our dayes as of old, Helpe vs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 85.8.</note> 
                     <hi>O God of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, for the glory of thy Name.</hi> Wherefore ſhould Papiſts ſay, It is for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that wee are thus plagued: wherefore ſhould Atheiſt ſay, Thou waſt not able to ſaue vs, &amp;c. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould carnall Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſay, What profit is it that thy people haue pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto thee, and walked <hi>mournefully before thee,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 21.14 Mal. 3.15</note> and <hi>It is in vaine to ſerue thee.</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:18937:95"/> And to the end thou maiſt continue the worke of our deliuerance, giue vs grace alſo to continue the worke of our humiliation before thee, vntill thou haue <hi>repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our Ieruſalem, the praiſe of our Nation;</hi> neuer <hi>letting thee go vntil thou haſt bleſſed vs,</hi> nor giuing thee reſt till thou haſt healed our Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Neither are we mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of it onely, but we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member other parts of our Land, beſeeching thee (good Lord) to ſtay thy hand from ſpreading the ſicknes in other Towns and Cities, and to withdraw it where it is diſperſt, giuing them all grace (according to their ſeueral conditions) by ſeaſonable amendment to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18937:95"/> preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or remoue the ſame; and in the mean time to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort al thoſe that any where are viſited with this or any other ſicknes, by recouering the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto health, to liue bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to thy glory, or by fitting them for death, to depart in peace to their ſaluation. Make an end of the tryall, (wee pray thee) of other Churches by the ſword, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or any other iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and continue to ours the peace of the Goſpel, &amp; the Goſpel of peace; preſeruing all Eſtates and degrees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, in Church and Common-wealth from this &amp; other plagues (if it be thy bleſſed will) to execute iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and to ſhew mercy, for the taking away of this,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18937:96"/> and the turning away of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heauy iudgements. Be thou <hi>exalted (Lord) in thine owne ſtrength, ſo will we ſing and praiſe thy power.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 21.16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>VI.</hi> Profeſſing our amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon our remou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the Plague.</note>For we doe not deſire (O Lord our God) to haue the plague of our ſicknes taken away from amongſt vs, that the plague of our ſinnes may remaine within vs, nor that thou ſhouldeſt turne thy heauie hand from vs, that wee might returne to our former wickednes, for <hi>the time paſt of our life is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient</hi> (and to much) <hi>to haue liued therein.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.3.</note> If thus <hi>againe we ſhould breake thy comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dements,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezera. 9.14</note> 
                     <hi>wouldſt thou not be angrie with vs till thou hadſt conſumed vs:</hi> but wee beg this further favour of thee,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18937:96"/> 
                     <hi>not to die,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. 118.17</note> 
                     <hi>but to liue to declare thy works</hi> and to praiſe thy name.<note place="margin">Ier. 50.4.5</note> For this end <hi>with mourning and weeping</hi> for our former many and grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinnes, <hi>wee come vnto thee and ſeeke thee,</hi> and will <hi>ioyne our ſelues vnto thee in a</hi> perpetuall <hi>couenant neuer to be forgotten.</hi> Wee <hi>will make a couenant bef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e thee our God, to walke after thee, &amp; to keepe thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, thy ſtatutes and thy teſtimonies with all our hearts, and with all our ſoules, nnd to performe the words of the couenant,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Reg. 23.3</note> 
                     <hi>and to ſtand vnto it,</hi> wee will <hi>make a ſure couenant &amp; write it and ſeale vnto it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Neh. 9.38.</note> yea wee <hi>will enter into a curſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an oath to walee in Gods lawe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Neh. 10.29</note> 
                     <hi>and to obſerue and to do
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18937:97"/> all the commandemnts of the Lord our God</hi> that we may ty our looſe <hi>harts</hi> to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thy holy wil for euer And let our houſes which thou haſt viſited or kept cleare from this contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and let our bodies, which thou haſt healed or preſerued from infection, and let our ſoules which thou haſt humbled &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in any meaſure by and vnder this viſitation, beare witnes to our ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in making this holy vow and couenant with thee. Let them bee a continuall remembrance to put vs in minde of often renewing it before thee: and let them bee as a <hi>threefold cord not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily broken</hi> faſter to binde
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18937:97"/> vs to the keeping of this oath &amp; couenant with thee for euer. And now (O Lord our God) ſince thou haſt by thy Spirit put into our hearts this deſire to giue thee thanks, &amp; direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vs to this means of mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting our thankfulnes we humbly beſeech thee <hi>keepe it for euer in the thoughts and imaginations of the hearts of thy people,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Chr. 29 15.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſet our hearts vnto thee, And giue vs ſuch a heart that wee may feare thee, &amp; keepe thy commandements alwayes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deu. 5.29.</note> 
                     <hi>that it may bee well with vs and with our children for euer, ſo wee thy people and ſheepe of thy paſture will giue thee praiſe for euer, &amp; will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bee ſetting forth thy praiſe from generation to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,</hi> Amen.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18937:98"/>
                  <p>Now vnto the <hi>King immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, inuiſible and onely true God,</hi> moſt mighty &amp; wiſe, faithfull and true, patient and pittifull, gracious &amp; mercifull, infinite in all perfection; <hi>The Father of mercy,</hi> in <hi>The Sonne of peace,</hi> through <hi>The Holy Spirit of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> be yeelded and giuen for all our former and later deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerances in this or any other kind; and namely, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtaying of the Plague, (happily in great meaſure al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready begun and continued, and hopefully in the end to be perfected &amp; accompliſhed) From our beliefe &amp; truſt; our loue and feare; our hope and ioy; our patience &amp; obedience with our bodies and ſoule, by our thoughts, words, &amp; works in our liues and deaths: all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory, and all praiſe &amp; thanks, from this time forth and for euer.<note place="margin">Pſ. 106.48</note> And <hi>let all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſay,</hi> AMEN</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:98"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18937:99"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
